public hearing. Sycamore Ridge. Uh we
have attorney Albert who will conduct
the public hearing for this evening.
before the planning commission gets it
a
Can you hear me in the back?
Testing, testing.
Okay,
>> does this one work?
Okay. Can
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Can you hear me now?
>> A little bit. Okay. A little bit too
well. Okay. We'll start from the top
before the planning commission gets to
its u traditional uh agenda items. We
have one special item tonight. Uh
pursuant to uh the flexible residential
development option uh contained in the
city zoning ordinance, the planning
commission has uh jurisdiction over
flexible residential development plans
which is what has been submitted here
and which we are considering tonight. Uh
the applicant has requested preliminary
and final plan approval.
Uh what will happen is here is that this
is u because this board makes decisions
rather than recommendations. This
particular hearing will be in a more
formal way than planning commission
meetings are generally run. This will be
run more like a zoning hearing in which
u witnesses will be sworn in uh and we
will receive testimony in a more formal
fashion than the kind of free discussion
that goes on in planning commission
proceedings. Uh we will hear from the
applicant first since the applicant has
the burden proof. The u commission may
certainly ask questions. I may have some
questions. The audience will be given an
opportunity to ask questions. Uh the
city it's my course is always a party to
a proceeding in its jurisdiction and I
believe the city uh will have testimony
regarding this application and we'll
hear from anybody else who wants to be
heard. Um I once will say that if you
feel that someone else has made your
point we the board does not really need
Again, if your point hasn't been made,
then we'll be happy to hear it. But, um,
you know, we we do want to, uh, avoid
repetitious testimony if we can. Um,
okay. As you are probably aware, we're
starting a little bit late because the
board conducted an executive session
with me. That's a prerogative of, uh,
zoning hearings where the board is
allowed to meet with the solicitor
privately to get legal advice on how the
case will go. Um,
After the board hears the case this
evening, the board may very well wish to
conduct another executive session. In
that case, the board will adjourn to a
private room upstairs where it can
consult with me, discuss the case among
themselves, and hopefully after that
come to a vote. Uh the options are to
grant final plan approval, to grant
preliminary plan approval, to agree to
continue this case within the time
requirements of
Planning code or to deny the plan
because it's incomplete. If there would
be a denial of the plan on the basis
that it's incomplete, that is not a
ruling on the merits of the case. It's
simply saying that at this time we don't
feel uh the formalities of the flexible
residential development option ordinance
have been met and the applicant will
have the right to come back at a later
date with a more complete plan. Uh if we
do take an executive session, I'm
mindful that there's other business and
we'll try to do that as quickly as we
can, but that may be the case. U before
I begin, I would ask uh Lauren Finn uh
was uh are you aware of whether the
agenda was put on the city website and
was availed on the building here at
least 24 hours before the hearing?
>> It was.
>> Thank you very much. And are copies of
the agenda available here for the
public?
>> Yes. Thank you. That's a formality of
the Sunshine Act that we need to comply
with. Okay. On that basis, then uh
unless there's any questions about how
we'll proceed, I will turn the case over
to the applicant and whoever is going to
be presenting the case, the applicant,
please identify yourself to the court
reporter and you will be sworn a
proceed.
Turning this on everybody hear me? Okay.
Well, uh, good evening, planning
commissioner ers and members of the
public. Um, my name is Joe Mugabo. My
business partner uh here is Mark
Peteritis. We are longtime residents of
Langster County and together we own uh
MPL Holdings. Over the next 15 minutes,
we're excited to return to the planning
commission to update you on how the plan
for uh Sycamore Ridge in Sunnyside has
progressed since we last presented to
you um our sketch plan. And while we
still have much to do, we are seeking
approval of this tenative plan
submission so that we can continue it
continuing moving it forward in the
process for a final plan.
There's been a lot of buzz around
Sunnyside Peninsula recently and we
think that's really great. Much of that
uh started with the city comprehensive
plan roll out and a huge theme as
illustrated in green here uh is the
adopted land use map is committing heavy
investment in supporting outdoor wreck
and revitalization of the Knosa River.
We're already seeing the exciting
beginnings of a na nature preserve
environmental center and starting to
take shape on the northern portion of
the peninsula and on the southern
portion uh in Sunnyside Hashton yellow
here on the screen
uh includes a future land use overlay
for a residential eco district and while
most people don't even know what an eco
district is um I think it's accurate to
take
it's an accur accurate take on the
intent that it is to inspire developers
like us to think outside the box,
ensuring that the residential portion of
Sunnyside stays special, stays unique,
not just generic housing for the sake of
housing.
So, we truly believe in the overall
comprehensive plan and the vision of the
for the peninsula as it um as long as it
does not forget the key ingredient,
which is people.
Sunnyside really needs a community of
people, invested homeowners that can
sustainably live and thrive on the
peninsula.
After all, what what good is a nature
preserve or anything really if there's
no people there to enjoy it?
So there's it's no secret the peninsula
has accumulated a history of nuisance uh
land uses over the years due to poor
planning and you know housing is housing
and forest have been replaced with
limestone quarry and salvage facility
juvenile detention center. People live
here too but certainly not ideal.
There's a lot to undo.
And although the city hasn't adopted any
regulation to support a change in zoning
from current R3 to eco district,
achieving success will not will not be
about conforming Sunnyside to typical
city ordinances. It will be just the
opposite, requiring both a developer
with a unique vision and a planning
staff that is willing to boldly guide
them beyond conformity.
So, two years ago, I tested this theory.
I had the honor of standing in front of
you to earn approval for the first land
development project on the Sunnyside
Peninsula in over a century, literally
101 years later. We built a pair of 800
square foot riverside cottages. You can
find them at twinsycamore.com.
They are short-term rentals, and our
family really enjoys going down and
appreciating the neighborhood as well,
but very uniquely designed for Sunnyside
as a nod to the original vision
um
original vision of the neighborhood when
it was first developed in 1912.
This land was uh the plan was
unanimously approved and it was even
applauded not because it conformed
perfectly to city ordinances. It didn't.
It was approved because of the care and
thoughtfulness that went into ensuring
that they fit. Uh we took we fit the our
project into the existing fabric of what
makes Sunnyside magical.
And for city planners, that's the mark
of true leadership. By supporting this
project, they weren't sacrificing safety
or quality. They saw that while
Sunnyside was a city neighborhood,
it certainly didn't look anything like
the city.
They rightly saw that as a good thing
and ultimately helped us get relief on
ordinances that were just not
applicable.
I think it's also important to
understand the difference between
building codes and standards and
ordinances. Building codes provide
engineered direction on how to create
roads or structures that don't fail.
It's what keeps us safe. We we don't
want to mess with these. These are these
are non-negotiables. But ordinances on
the other hand are local laws. designed
to help municipalities create uniformity
beyond building code, ensuring roads,
structures look and feel specific ways
that conform to their objectives and
goals.
So, thanks to you and the work of the
staff, our small little project down
here came to fruition and ended up being
a really great success on multiple
levels.
These homes really do fit in. We've
enjoyed getting to know our neighbors.
Many of them are are here tonight.
Sunnyers are some of the kindest the
nicest people I have ever met and I'm
proud to be a part of this community.
But it's also been a bit con convicting.
I mean, there's a lot to do down here,
which is why we felt led and qualified
to take on this much larger project.
Our vision for Sycamore Ridge was
heavily inspired by Mount Greta, a
thriving woodland retreat in Lebanon
County.
A lot of the original 1912 vision for
Sunnyside and Rocky Springs feel very
similar to what they're what's going on
at Mount Greta. And I think it's the
closest example we could find at least
locally to what an equitable eco
district might even look like in
Sunnyside.
I mean, could you imagine if instead of
building Juvie Center, Junkyard and
Corey, if somebody decided to build
Mount and Sunnyside all those
years ago, how different things would
be.
In addition to Mount Gretina, Ross
Chapen and his book Pocket Neighborhoods
really uh were a big inspiration for us
as well. We ended up hiring Ross as a
consultant to help us with our site
design. And Pocket Neighborhoods, just
for explain what that is, it's a group
of houses clustered around shared open
space. Uh it's not a one-sizefits-all
thing. They can vary in shape and size,
but ultimately they're designed to pro
to protect um to provide a protected
environment for people to live and be
outside in nature, engage with their
neighbors.
So, put those inspirations together and
this is what we came up with. This is
Sycamore Ridge and Sunnyside. The vision
of Sycamore Ridge is blending
Sunnyside's existing woodland community
infrastructure with the added charm of
modernday Mount Gretina and the
lifestyle and feel of a pocket
neighborhood all right here in the city.
This will be a unique residential nature
community that respects the history of
the one before it, yet boldly leads by
example through thoughtful design and
sustainable future.
And similar to our twin Sycamore
cottages, this housing will be smaller
and more energy efficient than most new
home construction. They're simple but
elegant homes built with locally locally
sourced materials, making them easy to
maintain, enjoyable to live in.
We define this as sustainable market
rate housing that's affordable by
design.
They will be available for sale and they
will generate over a million dollars per
year in combined tax base of the city,
school district, and county. It's a big
deal.
And they will they'll be mixed uh
there'll be a mix of single family
detached and semi- detached units that
are two and threebedroom layouts with
floor plans ranging in between 12 and
1,800 square f feet.
Two off- streetet parking spaces will be
uh will be there as well with a
combination of integrated driveways and
garages. There will also be main floor
living concepts available for 55 plus
and multi-gen living.
These homes will also be heated and
cooled with renewable geothermal
systems, which is just one of the many
eco district design components we've
integrated within our plan and outlined
in our consistency letter.
We've taken a holistic approach to
sustainability and incorporated design
elements that address low lower energy,
improve living systems, reduce water,
reduce waste, improves wellness, and all
contributing to an equitable community.
Here's the site plan we presented to to
you guys the last time we were here.
And just to orient everybody, north is
to the uh to the left of the screen. So
that's where like the environmental
center, the quarry would be. On the
right side of the screen is where Duke
Street would be. So in preparation for a
day, I I went back and watched the
sketch plan presentation we had on
YouTube, and I got to tell you, I I was
really excited and uh encouraged by the
energy you guys had uh in the remarks.
Your recommendations were very good
ones, and we took them to heart.
So, this is what we've come up with
since we've been here last. And I know
this is very hard to see right here. So,
we we made a a little bit more of a
presentation uh version to look at while
we talk, but by far the number one
recommendation when we were here last,
you guys wanted to remove that parking
lot from the center of our our our area,
and we did it. And while we're we
weren't able to remove the entire cart
path due to fire safety and ADA access
to our clubhouse, we made it as small as
possible. It's a 14 foot one-way alley
with no purpose other than to enhance
community interaction.
The overall guest parking has also been
reduced from the original 30 spaces to
now 16 which are all now dispersed
throughout the development and not just
in one place. Giving purpose uh also
giving purpose as some are even equipped
with EV chargers and hookups suitable
for food trucks and uh and service
trucks for community events and
neighborhood programming.
As for your feedback around
strengthening the infrastructure for
community uh recreation activities,
our plan now has again clubhouse with a
designated ADA parking community garden,
numerous pavilions, park benches,
sitting areas, large open spaces for
free play, a natural amphitheater, and
one of my favorites, a primitive play
area similar to what's installed at the
new school on Columbia Avenue.
I'll touch a little bit more on on this
later, but the addition of self storage
is also now a component of our community
infrastructure
um as it's tied specifically to
recreation, getting people outside and
allowing for smaller and therefore more
affordable eco-friendly housing.
And lastly, you asked us to consider
creative ways of providing more density.
The short answer is we have and it's
this is the best we can do. Uh first and
foremost, of the 79 units that are shown
here, 69 of them are duplexed. So
they're they are this single family
detached.
69 of the Yeah. So there's 10 left over.
The second main uh obstacle here is that
public works has only provided us a
willingness to serve for sewage capacity
for the 79 units here shown.
So, here is the same plan uh that you
were just looking at, just a bit more
zoomed out to help you get a little bit
bigger picture spatially. You can see my
big red arrow there. That's the South
Duke Street Bridge.
And just after that on the left, there
are four city streets going into
Sunnyside. Remember, this is this is not
a cornfield in the middle of nowhere.
This is an existing neighborhood. And
while there's only 35 or 40 houses back
here currently, it was originally
developed in and engineered with
hundreds of lots.
So therefore, access to Sycamore Ridge
will simply mirror the same main entry
points via South Duke Street. One by way
of Davis Street, shown in green, the
other Parkway to Circle shown in orange,
which will ultimately um is and will
continue to uh be the main connector for
Pleasant Street uh shown in blue there.
Davis would specifically connect
travelers to south and the eastmost
sides of the development and Parkway
would connect travelers to the north and
westmost sides of the development. So if
you were to drive into Sunnyside on
Davis using the green line, you'd first
pass a few residential homes and then
right before getting to our new
development,
you'd pass Sunnyside Menite Church on
your left.
Believe it or not,
beyond our property and cities,
Sunnyside Monite Church is actually the
next largest land owner on the
peninsula.
Over the years, they have strategically
accumulated neighboring lots and even
portions of Parkway, as you can see here
in the red,
in anticipation for possible future
expansion opportunities that they might
have. And because of this, we took that
very seriously. We we included them in
over six months of our planning and
discussions post sketch plan that we met
with you. Numerous uh entry alternatives
were proposed with the church and staff
which ultimately resulted in this
configuration.
And as you can see, existing public
rightways for Davis and Pleasant Street,
shown in the yellow there,
have been utilized and reoriented to
achieve proper entry to Sycamore Ridge,
but also their church off of Davis
without involving any of their property.
And this allows us to maintain proper
street grades, which was a problem last
time we were having LA last time we met
with you. Um, existing utility
connections, but it's great that we also
can still room to install nine new
parking spaces for the church. We're
committed to being a good neighbor here
and are eager to see their mission
thrive and grow in the future as well.
And while I'm here, this is a good time,
I think, to also highlight the
transition of public to private streets.
It's a little odd, I know, for that to
happen in the city, but the green
represents existing public streets, and
there's existing residents here, too. So
in the yellow you can see there there's
existing residences that that need to
maintain public access. So that's a lot
of the reason we designed the way the
streets the way we did. In the blue you
can see where the streets transition to
private and of course that's after um
after those homes.
And to be clear the streetscape in
Sunnyside currently looks like this. So
among other things like storm water
volume control and a lot of different
the look and feel of these streets, the
size of these streets, privatizing them
is very intentional as it provides from
an ordinance perspective the opportunity
for us to maintain the same woodland
alley like look and feel that's already
seen throughout the neighborhood.
All right, I'm almost almost done
finishing up this little tour. We have
my little red arrow here that is just
about where this rendering is has a
perspective. So this is the eastmost
streetscape through Sycamore Ridge and
it's a continuation of the Davis Street.
So heading north along the wooded ridge
line overlooking the Knosogga River and
the the first house here on the on the
left is actually unit 41 on our site
plan. It backs up to and is
traditionally kind of a pocket
neighborhood feel. So, it has uh the
back opens up to a beautiful open uh
space and has a very a pavilion close
by.
The the first house on the right is
number 13 on our site plan and it has an
amazing view. It's lofted up on on the
cliff and uh really dense mature forest
overlooking the Knosa River. It's
absolutely gorgeous. People will want to
one one or the other. There's a lot of
things here, but I think what I I wanted
to showcase here is that while number 13
on the right doesn't necessarily conform
to a typical pocket neighborhood
concept, it's still intimately connected
due to our thoughtfully
uh done trail system in lie of just
street sidewalks.
So, going back to the site plan, you can
see my little red arrow and unit 13 up
there. I mean, look how close it is to
everything.
Within less than 40 yards, you can walk
to the clubhouse and pick up your mail.
Or maybe you're meeting up with a guest
if you live in, you know, unit 13, meet
up at a pavilion for dinner, and your
guests can pull up and charge their cars
while while they're having dinner with
you. Maybe residents of number 13 have a
garden plot, and that's a quick walk as
well. And instead of only having a small
window of time that matches your kids
attention span like mine,
they actually are you could actually get
some quality gardening done because the
kids can roam free here and hang out at
the park in a very safe environment.
Residents of number 13 might also love
mountain biking or the trails in the
county park or maybe even the new trails
at the nature preserve. You can see my
little red arrow there. They they simply
could walk down to the storage unit,
grab their bikes, and go.
And as alluded to earlier, in addition
to the housing component, we've also
been approved by zoning to install a
small amount of self storage. And while
out of context this might seem a little
odd, I assure you it's not. It's very
intentional. This is a an older
rendering that we have, but I think it
really does a good job showcasing just
how thoughtfully integrated this
offering will be for the development,
both functionally and aesthetically.
We're excited about this because it not
only meets the storage need of our
smaller housing stock, but it also
caters to the many outdoor enthusiasts
in the city right now and in the future,
allowing them to store bikes, kayaks,
canoes, all within walking distance of
future public river access, greenway
trails, and even the county park nearby.
You get the picture. This is going to be
awesome.
But as beautiful and all as all
inspiring as this all is, what you see
in this rendering here couldn't be
farther from conforming to Lancaster
city ordinance.
We were very upfront with this the first
time we came and stood before you and is
still very much the case today.
Everything from city streets, uh, from
the street widths, the curbs, sidewalks,
and the way our storm water is even
managed,
it's all been customized to blend in the
new with the old with as little sight
disturbance as possible. And as you
probably saw in our letter, this is not
something that city staff is used to
seeing every day. Their job is typically
to ensure plan submissions conform to
ordinances.
This one literally is designed
intentionally not to conform.
So in the last two minutes of uh
our presentation, I wanted to and of
course before we open up to questions, I
wanted to ask Douglas Smith, who some of
you know, to offer a few closing
comments about the project and its path
forward as we enter in the process.
Thank you.
Uh, thank you Joe. Good evening,
planning commission, members of the
public, friends, colleagues, esteemed
former mayors, chiefs of staff,
developers, other dignitaries. Uh my
name is Douglas Smith. I'm a certified
urban planner and serving as consultant
for the Sycamore Ridge project. Uh
previously, I worked for the city of
Lancaster for 10 years on a variety of
community development and infrastructure
projects and most recently held the
position as chief planner uh for the
city. I now work for the US Green
Building Council as director of location
land use where I advise on
sustainability policy for a variety of
um environmental certification products.
Um I'd like to offer some closing
thoughts on this project and thank you
Joe for and Mark for having me. Um
during my 10 years with the city, I
helped oversee a historic level of
investment. Uh during that time, nearly
every development project required
waiverss, modifications, negotiations,
and novel strategies to get the job
done. Um whether it was affordable
housing, a hospital expansion, or a
small commercial facility, um nearly
every one of them received some kind of
relief from the planning commission or
another board. Um so I just wanted to
set that context in terms of what the
historic trajectory has been in terms of
accomplishing uh projects in the city.
And I I don't think that this project um
is any different in the way that it it
needs some u a unique solution. Although
the particular context here might be a
little bit different.
So I'd like to pick up on one of the
last things that uh Joe said about how
this project doesn't neatly conform to
standard ordinances. Um, Sycamore Ridge
is pursuing the flexible residential
development option and uh for that
reason uh because of the zoning
ordinance section 300-23 is intended
among other things to allow innovations
and creativity within the tract
regarding arrangement of structures,
dwellings and related infrastructure and
sorry I missed the first part there. Uh
to allow for development on lots with
physical constraints such as steep
slopes. Um, this project undoubtedly
meets this uh the intent of this section
of the ordinance. Um, so this special
filing was designated for these kinds of
unique projects and it gives the
planning commission special powers to
help provide relief. Um, so we're
inviting you all the planning commission
to think outside the box with us and
consider uh what might need to be done
differently on this project.
Flexible residential development is
typically accomplished as a tenative
plan followed by a final plan uh with
one caveat. Um small text there and I'll
just paraphrase for you. Uh the planning
commission holds the power to approve a
tenative plan as a final plan if it
meets all the requirements of a final
application. I want to make clear to the
commission uh this evening that we're uh
we'd like to take a different tact on
this. Um, we've revised, we'd like to
revise our request and ask you to
consider a tenative plan approval. Um,
instead, um, this, uh, will help us, um,
have your reassurance, uh, or your your
buyin from the planning commission so
that we can proceed with addressing the
more technical comments with the city
with with more confidence.
>> Excuse me, sir. Can you repeat the
revision of your request? I'm not sure I
follow.
>> Sure. So uh the agenda advertised that
the developer was seeking to forego a
tenative plan and seek a final plan
approval. So in lie of that um the
revised request is that the planning
commission consider a tenative plan
approval.
>> Okay.
>> Rather than going straight to final. Um
it was it was listed under
modifications. I don't think that's
technically a modification, but just
wanted to make clear that uh we're we're
changing our request on the
>> I agree with you.
>> Okay. Thank you for clarifying.
Um, now I want to touch on the planning
process just for a moment. Um, I've
grouped these decision by
decision-making body, not as a timeline,
but I want to let you know that uh this
project has been before the zoning
hearing board and has uh achieved a
special exception for self storage. Um,
the county planning commission is
scheduled to review this project on
October 14th for uh consistency with its
use land use plan at the county level.
Um, city planning commission, you all
have been involved in the sketch plan.
We appreciate all your comments there.
You heard from Joe on that. Uh tonight
is satisfying the tenative plan public
hearing which is required. And then uh
the last one on that list would be um
seeking um tenative conditional plan
approval by November 16th which is 60
days after the public hearing ends if it
ends tonight. Um and uh then that would
that actually the meeting that would
have to be heard at would be November
5th. Um so that's the next planning
commission meeting before this date. uh
passes. I'm sorry I have the date wrong
on it says 9:17, but Oh, yeah, it is.
Yeah, sorry. That's correct. Um, okay.
So, moving on to just a couple of final
things. Uh, I wanted to give you a peek
at what's coming next. Um, if this plan
were to proceed. So, this is these are
some of the approvals that are needed
for the final uh plan process. Um, there
are a couple of state approvals needed
for sewage and for storm water. Um both
the shade tree commission and traffic
commission would be required to review
this plan and take action on it as well.
That typically comes towards the end of
the final plan uh process so that we
have all of our details um uh you know
straight and city has reviewed things.
Um we have other approvals from PPL
electric too. City council also needs to
act on portions of this plan. they would
be approving the planning module for
sewage um any street dedication or
vacation and potentially um other
agreements if that if those are
required. And then finally, the planning
commission here would be reviewing um
the plan as well probably once at least
once or maybe two times uh followed by
an action on it. Um so that's the
trajectory that we're we're looking at
here. Um and uh I would encourage you to
learn more about the project. scan the
QR code, go to the website, sign up for
updates. Um, couple of final closing
thoughts before we open up to questions,
and I'm sorry I've exceeded my two
minutes that I was allotted. Um, when I
started working at the city, I reviewed
the last Sunnyside plan that some of you
may remember. Um, that project, um,
although had different kinds of benefits
than this one, it did propose clear
cutting most of the forest on the
peninsula, installing 350 units on the
peninsula, building to the edges of the
flood plane, hardly providing any
recreational area for residents, and in
my opinion, not much of a forwardinking
environmental vision. Um, I held these
lessons in mind while I served as one of
the primary authors for the city
planning commission's adoption of the
comprehensive plan and I helped
brainstorm with residents, staff, and
this commission about the future of
Sunnyside. And that vision that we all
came to collectively um included an
environmentally friendly development
like Sycamore Ridge and an environmental
center. And that vision has captured the
imagination of the community and
attracted potentially millions of
dollars from the High Foundation and
others. Um and I really see Sycamore
Ridge as trying to achieve that vision
and uh does require doing things a bit
differently. Um and I'm encouraged by
that. So, I'm glad to be here tonight
and see you all and I look forward to
listening carefully to all your
comments. Thank you.
>> Does the applicant have any other
witnesses?
>> Okay. Uh, normally this would be the
time where the commission would throw
this open for questions. It has been my
experience in 50 years of doing this
that people who attend these hearings
seldom ask questions. They ask the
question and then they go right into
making their statement for or against.
So to avoid that kind of chaos, what
we're going to do is hear from the city
of Lancaster next who is a party and has
a position statement and then we will
throw it open for questions, comments,
anything you want to do. So if you bear
with us for just a moment, folks, you
will have you will have a chance to be
heard. This is a public hearing.
Everyone will get their say
at this point. I would City of Lancaster
have any representative present?
>> Yes, this is Betsy Logan. I'm the
planning bureau chief for the city.
>> Okay, reporter, please.
>> Um, thank you. Yes. So, the city um
staff has reviewed the submitt for the
tenative review of Sycamore Ridge and um
while the administr administration has
been working with the um applicants on
Sycamore Ridge at Sunnyside at this
point, there are some elements that are
lacking in the submission that need to
be addressed prior to final plan
approval. Um because it is a specific
flexible residential development, there
are numerous requirements that still
need to be met even though it is to
provide flexibility on development. Um
we have provided the um applicant with
our staff report outlining
um numerous issues that we are not able
to provide feedback like more detailed
feedback on because we're still unclear
as to what solution would be or to how
they're proposing to do certain things.
>> In what respects is the application
incomplete?
>> So, well, they submitted all the
specific criteria that's required um
there's not enough detail on um
storm water, sewer, um water lines. Uh
there's some more information that's
needed for zoning. Um and uh
it's kind of hard to
>> provide a full length of all the
>> well uh if if the if this board has to
make if this board is to take action uh
the board either for well preliminary
plan approval because final plan
approval is off the table for the night.
The board first of all has to satisfy
itself whether or not the application is
complete and ready for consideration.
And if the city has a view that it's not
uh the specific reasons would need to be
placed on the record so the board can
make an informed decision.
>> Sure. So um some of the zoning issues
that are outlined in the letter are
related to the calculation for density.
>> Excuse me. By by the letter Are you
referring to a letter of September 8th,
you?
>> Yes. Um it was prepared um by CSD
Davidson as well as um our general group
of people who do
um review which includes uh public works
right away um environmental concerns um
storm water
uh sewer water zoning general
subdivision and land development. Um so
all of those people have reviewed
>> okay and based on that letter what are
the city's specific concerns about the
incompleteness of this application?
So um zoning wise there are some
questions on parking calculations and
how they were determined as well as
building density calculations. Um in
addition as part of a flexible
residential design architectural
renderings are required and we did not
receive
>> slow
people can read a lot faster than the
court.
>> Okay. and um architectural rendings are
required for the self- storage
buildings.
Um
there are some concerns regarding well I
guess the biggest um concern that we
have is as submitted the application
included um three properties that
currently the city of Lancaster owns. Um
back in
Jul J January of this year um we had
conversations with the applicant
regarding the potential to swap
properties. Um in February the
applicant's attorney received
information from our solicitor that at
this time the city was not interested in
doing that but those properties were
still included in this application.
Okay. Um, for planning comments, the
developer needed to submit the written
response to all the sketch plan comments
that wasn't received with the
application. Um, and they need to
address the changes as Joe outlined in
his presentation. Like that would need
to be addressed in writing as a sketch
plan review. um comment letter.
>> Okay. That that was uh that was in 2024.
>> Yes, it was dated September 16th, 2024.
>> Anything else?
>> Um
as far as what's missing from being able
to make a decision on it, we the sewage
planning module um has not been
submitted yet. We would need HOA
documents to review and including
documents that outline how the
commercial self storage is going to be
working. Um we don't have sewer and
water um will serve letters. They were
not provided with the application.
Um profiles on roads, water, storm sewer
and sewer were not provided
um
which would be needed in order and
additionally cross road crosssections
were not included to ensure compliance
with um the subdivision and land
development. There was a request for a
waiver um to reduce the length of how
frequently the profiles to be provided
um that is included in this application.
>> I'm sorry.
>> Sorry. There's a request for a waiver
related to how many profiles I need to
provide.
um that was included in their
application.
>> Okay. Was that waiver acted upon or was
that for for the commission?
>> That's for the planning commission.
>> Okay.
What's the city's position on whether
that waiver should be granted?
>> Um in our discussion regarding it, we
don't feel that it should be granted
because um of the
um steepness of the property. We would
like to see more consistent profiles
which would be in any application.
>> Uh you'll have to I'm not an engineer.
You'll have to explain to me why the
statements of the property relates to
the number of crosssections you want to
see.
>> I'm also not an engineer so I don't know
that I can provide feedback on that.
>> Fair enough.
We'll get
going as far as why you feel
Um, as far as being incomplete, there
are concerns with um, over the past year
as we've worked with the applicant um,
they had gone away from the Davis Street
entrance. So, we've had numerous
conversations related to um, expanding
the parkway entrance and as access um,
when they did come to submit the plan
that went back to Davis Street. So those
conversations that were had um that kind
of had a process outlined and what
needed to be provided um changed and so
there's not enough detail on what
they're proposing
for the Davis entrance.
Um water and sewer comments um would
include there's a water line that would
need to be provided to address proper
fireflow pressure. We've been working
the applicant on where that should be
located coming from the partners for
environmental stewardship and the city
property that was not provided on the
plan. Um
survey of the city's existing sanitary
sewer facilities around the project area
is also needed to be provided. Um there
are concerns too regarding the um
downstream capacity of the city's
sanitary sewer.
Um, another concern that we have is that
um, a phase one or phase 2 environmental
study were not provided as part of the
submission. They did reference it in
some of their documentation. However, we
have not seen any of that and the
remediation for that needs to be um,
more detailed.
Is a phase two environmental study
required by the application?
>> I could not answer that question
specifically. Um, generally we tend to
require it if there if we know that
there's environmental concerns with
digging and it used to be a um scrapard
for automobiles.
>> Has one been requested?
>> It was included in the letter.
>> Okay.
Um there's several storm water concerns.
Um the biggest one being that the
modeling um didn't look at the correct
storm flow events
and the correct um runoff. I think they
need to do 1.25 and that was what was
provided.
That's generally what we feel is what's
missing from the application.
>> Um, not at this time.
>> The letter of September 8th. Um,
okay. 2025. That letter was that letter
shared with the applicant?
>> Yes, it was provided to the applicant on
September 8th.
>> Okay.
Did you receive any formal respon any
response to that?
>> Um, we had a follow-up meeting regarding
the letter um, Monday of this week,
the 15th and then another follow-up
meeting yesterday with the applicant.
What is the city's position regarding
this application?
>> At this time, the city does not believe
that it's ready for tenative land
development approval. There's some large
questions that need to be considered,
especially considering it's a plan
residential development process and has
very specific requirements that need to
be met before the city could take action
on approving anything.
Before
we open up to the audience, I'm
certainly going to give the applicant a
chance to respond to
whoever wants to speak.
Let's hear from them.
So we um we very much understand that
there's a lot of work to be done. I
think part of these larger projects um
Douglas mentioned a lot of items um like
shape to recommission HOAs. There's a
lot of things that traditionally are
left to final plan submission there.
There's a lot of detail going on in this
project and in any project this size.
And so um some of the we got this
September 8th. Um again, did not get a
whole lot of time to review or get back
and forth. We're talking about two days
ago.
Um so yes, there are things that, you
know, everybody has this information.
There are there are items that we need
to discuss and figure out. our our
engineers have been looking at it um
talking to their engineers.
I'm a glass half full guy. I don't think
any of these issues are issues that are
going to stop the project. Um where
there's a will, there's a way. And there
seems to be a way. It it's just going to
take time. And so I think with the the
concept of the flexible land development
plan, we chose this route because it
seemed like the only route that made
sense to do something so
out of the ordinary. The comp the
comprehensive plan calls for it to be
out of the ordinary. And so if we showed
up today with a a formal preliminary
plan and we were asking you to vote on
it,
there's no way that you should say yay.
It's not complete as a preliminary plan
in the formal sense, but a tenative
plan. Absolutely. I think it's far
enough along the storm water, for
instance, we far exceed certain ideas.
I'm not an engineer, so I'm not going to
go into detail either. Um Betsy and I
are not engineers, but what we do know
is that our engineers have looked at it.
They have been talking to each other,
and there is a path. And um yeah, so
anyway, I I don't want to take too much
time on this. We can dive into specific
items if we need to, but all of these
items are very very achievable.
There's no way we'd be able to walk
through each of these
holding holding the the timeline legal
timeline that the tenative plan has. And
so I think the flexibility of this route
allows for us to get tenative approval,
allows us to keep moving, keep getting
things done, just checking
systematically checking things off the
list. Um this is not an approval of a
final plan in any way, shape or form and
is not prepared as a final plan in any
shape or form.
You guys have any comments beyond that?
questions at this time
the city or the
>> uh yeah I just I guess one of the
questions I mean over here
no problem um so you know for the the
example of the city owned properties
that you include in your plan I mean
that seems like a pretty big deal if you
can't get those properties so I'm just c
like there I totally understand you know
that you're requesting some flexibility
and I think you know as a planning
commission we're we're definitely uh
interested in that conversation but for
like those are that's a pretty big
issue. Um so for the bigger issues could
you give us some context?
>> Yeah specifically for the the land swap
um that was honestly a mistake on our
part. We we don't have a full-time
attorney dedicated to this project.
There is no attorney representing us
today and we're doing that uh very
intentionally. This is it's a very
unique project. U so we wanted to be
delicate and personal with this. Um our
attorney
apparently received this notification in
February and we never got word of that.
Uh it sounds like a simple mistake. At
the same time, I have not had access to
the solicitor. I've not had access to
the mayor. I I don't know how much
conversation there has been at all about
these properties, but we can we can
bring them up, but they're they're three
very
um I don't want to say worthless because
they're valuable to somebody. Um but
they're they're
wooded cliff side that uh that's
unusable. any kind of um any kind of
development and it is weirdly tooththed
into our frontage. Um so it's certainly
worth with a phone call. We just haven't
had that phone call. And we we
specifically have three lots that are
very close to what seems to be where
like a the public access to the future
public access to the river and Corey
would be. Um that directly abuts a city
some city land as well. And we figured
like we have no purpose for these. I
think in the grander good of you know
the comprehensive plan I think they
would be really interested in those. So,
I don't know if we're buying or trading,
but I I think it's just a matter of a
conversation. I don't see why this
solicitor would want not do something
like that.
>> So, I guess just one followup is is your
how dependent is your plan on those
properties? Like, is there
>> It's not It's annoying. Again, it's a
mistake. Uh I'll be frank. It was a
mistake, but it's annoying. Yeah. So if
we can't get that done, we have to
redraw
massage around the layout. Okay. So
again, like I if I had access to the
mayor to ask, hey, would you
would you think this is a great idea?
Like I don't know what you're doing with
this, but it's just sitting here. We can
make some good use of it. And we have
those over here that I think you could
make really good use of. I think that's
really all it takes. If we get a no,
whatever. We just massage the
Um,
so I'm a little concerned with the lack
of the presentation to the city of the
environmental review. Um, I personally
feel that article one section 27 of the
constitution of Pennsylvania uh, which
makes the commonwealth a trustee of the
public natural resources also requires
the city in its perview to be a trustee
as well. So why have you not yet
disclosed that to the city?
>> I don't know what that is.
>> You're talking about the environmental
testing andor review or any of those.
>> Good evening, Mr. Dastra. Yeah, you're
talking about the uh I think the phase
one phase two environmental review. Um,
so there's some contamination on site
from the junkyard. Um, and I'll let Joe
me or Mark give you the updates on where
exactly that stands, but there's planned
or has been excavation there. And, uh,
so the phase one is is the assessment of
what contamination is there. The phase
two is the actual remediation of that
area. Um, all of that, the phase one is
done, the phase two will be underway and
that soil will be removed from the site.
Uh, which is of great benefit to the
community. Um it's uh beyond the storm
water infiltration requirements that
that the city may um ask us to prove
does not interfere with contaminants on
site. There's uh there's nothing in the
salo that I'm aware of that would
require us to provide the phase one and
phase two, but that was not
intentionally withheld for any
particular reason at all. And I think
we'd be happy to provide that all of
that documentation to the city. Um and
uh you know I think this project is um
very proud to be removing that
contamination that has been sitting in
the community for decades.
>> Okay. So applicants willing to give the
city those documents?
>> Yes. Yeah. We can provide those and and
just to give a quick summary we were
actually really pleasantly surprised
during our due diligence period of what
the testing showed. This very very minor
very small area and it's very minor. So,
um, yeah, the contamination that would
need to be removed is not something that
we were concerned with.
>> Okay, that's good. Um,
talking about the buildings themselves
and I don't know if you have anything to
say to this Mr. Smith because this would
now be your kind of area. Um, what is
the anticipated lead certification level
for these buildings?
>> Uh, none. And I know you don't want to
hear that. I really know that you don't
want to hear that, but um and Douglas
doesn't either.
It is expensive to do that and we are
trying so desperately hard to provide
affordable housing without subsidies,
without So yes, we could. It would just
make the price of these houses go up
even higher. And it just does not see
like a good idea. We already have such a
huge issue with affordability.
Uh and we're again the size, the
simplicity,
the design all around is intended to
bring the cost of new homes drastically
down.
That's the that's the real crux of why.
I mean, respectfully, in terms of cost,
I've heard it reported that you're
anticipating a 300,000 350,000 cost per
unit. Um that's already very expensive
for members of this community.
>> Exactly.
>> So
>> um that's a concern still. I I don't
think that quite adds up for me. Um
other so you had mentioned earlier that
local sourcing will make uh these units
easier to maintain and you know you're
talking about cost. Um how this might
sound like a big question but like how
does that logic hold? Like what is the
guarantee that loc sourcing the
materials also makes these easier to
maintain.
>> Um,
I'm not sure we want to pull pictures or
not, but the the material that we're I
use on the the cottages is what what we
use on pole barns like every day. It's
like the uh not so fancy standing seam
metal and um so it's very economical. Uh
there's lots of options for that and
it's practically maintenancefree the
last 50 plus years. We're using a lot of
that in a lot of creative ways. Um and
the the other items are you know just
kind of general wood sighting that is
you know has long duration guarantees
but again you know sitting on shelves
very liberally sourced. We have lots of
langsters als
accessing trusses and and building
materials. And so our our our houses are
literally designed with uh with the help
of our contractors. What can you get?
What can you get? How can we use this
product that you have access to? That's
how we built the last ones. That's how
we're going to build the new ones.
>> Okay. Um so it sounds more like it's
easy to maintain through simplicity of
design rather than the sourcing.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And the materials
themselves, I mean, just, you know, you
don't need to paint things. You don't
need to uh a lot of these materials
don't require a lot of maintenance. And
I think that's that's helpful for lots
of generations of of people, but yeah,
you had also said that you tested this
theory and it so it works. Um, as I
understand it, your existing units are
short-term rentals. So, how does those
two short-term rentals translate to the
success of a I'm counting 79 housing for
sale development complex. It's
completely different market. How how
does that translate to proving that this
is good?
>> Yeah, I think uh I think it's one of
those nuanced you can't quite put your
finger on it, but I I think it's a um it
was a a vision and an idea that we had.
Hey, can we make this work? And can we
embed something brand new? community and
it not be overwhelming.
Um, an alternative would be like we
could just go build like a 6,000 square
foot
wild crazy thing on on the cliff and I
don't know if that would jive right uh
that would not fit in at all.
Um, so I think to that respect that's
how we kind of are kind of deriving
success. The other like tangible just
can we do this? We again designed
thought through the building process but
uh the construction of those homes was
very efficient um which again has a
direct correlation to cost and so we're
we're we're taking those you know
learned processes and applying them too.
you had said that the wooded cliff side
is unusable. Uh I disagree with that
personally. In fact, I think that using
cliffsides can become a remarkably
a great use for ecological design, the
insulation the ground provides to the
structures you're building within. Um so
I I don't really have a question there.
I just want to state that for the record
that I I think that that doesn't hold
water. Uh the cliff sides are usable.
It's just you've made a choice to focus
on a different type of design. Um
I'll stop for a second if anybody else
has questions.
>> I have a number of questions regarding
the affordability of this project. You
have called this project an affordable
project a number of times. Um $350,000
starter home is not an affordable
starter home. Um we need to lessen the
um cost of housing within this
community. The average AMI of our
Lancaster city is $63,000.
a person making $63,000 cannot afford to
live in that housing development. Um on
top of that, I'm just curious to know um
self storage and some of the amenities
on this site. I heard the word HOA.
Curious to know what that would add um
to the cost of the housing particularly
itself. Um and then I would just
recommend that you remove the word
affordable um from this market rate
would be more appropriate. Um although
if you can get the prices down um I I
don't think that would happen because of
the capacity of the density.
Um
that's part of that's part of my spiel.
The other part is the um fire and safety
perspective of this. If I recall the
last time you gentlemen um stood in
front of us uh there were some serious
concerns regarding fire safety and
access to the water. uh the pressure
specifically if there were two fires on
either side of that community, which we
hope would never happen. Um currently,
it's my understanding that there is not
a way to um have capacity to serve both
of those homes depending on where
they're located. One of those hydrants
could only be running for at a time. So,
I'm curious to know a little bit more
about that. Um and I'll pause for a
second before I get to my next question.
>> Yeah, let's talk about building.
So,
let's jump in on on the fire uh safety
issue first because that's really
important. Um so, we we were flagged by
the um fire chief that was an issue that
there's in you know insufficient supply
as you noted and the solution for that
is to bring further supply from the
north end of the peninsula near the
Juvie Center where there is an 8 inch
main currently today. So we've been
talking with the the city team and with
the the high foundation associated with
the environmental center planning and
everything else to find a suitable route
to bring that down to solve that issue.
So it would need to be a condition for
this project to move forward.
>> Great.
>> Um how about the um let's back up one
second because I kind of tossed two
things at you at one time and I'm really
curious to go back to the affordability
aspect of this project. not so much just
as to um throw my thoughts out there,
but to get some thoughts back from you
gentlemen as well. Um you know, I do
have concerns um like I said regarding
your use of the word affordable. Um I
don't think that this is an affordable
first time housing project. I um but I'm
curious to know in addition to the
mortgage that somebody would be paying,
what additional costs would they have?
So, if I am a prospective resident of
your new community and I want to rent
one of your storage lockers, um what
will that cost me approximately? Um and
I'm also interested to know what my HOA
fees would potentially be um and what
would be included within that program.
>> Sure. So, for HOA, we're we're very
early in that, but we've estimated it to
be somewhere in the $80 range per month.
We're trying to keep that very low. We
don't have a tennis courts and that kind
of thing. Instead, we have outdoor
recreation as the main attraction
amenity. Um, so the goal is to keep it
under $100. Right now, we're planning
right around8 $85 a month. Um,
as far as storage, we haven't set
pricing or anything for that yet, but it
would be, you know, market rate or below
market rate. We'd have a variety of
sizes. It wouldn't be primarily
associated with cars. It would be
associated with small storage for bikes,
kayaks, you know, things of that nature.
>> And um
did you want do you want me to talk a
little bit about the affordability part?
Because I do think
>> well I I think if your minimum cost is
$300,000
just personally I take offense to you
using $300,000 homes in the word
affordability in the same sentence. That
is not
>> fair not a thing. So, it's all relative.
I appreciate that. I appreciate that the
the word affordable is directly
associated to subsidized and I
appreciate that being um the issue. Um
affordable is also relative. The the
average regular home in Lancaster City,
I think was 386 last time I saw L&P and
the average new home is 488.
So, Lancaster County right now. So
affordable based on those terms is
absolutely affordable,
but we will try to slow that down or use
another word.
>> I just think it's really important that
we buy that we are manufacturing
realistic housing for the population
that we're actually serving. Um
>> I can appreciate that.
>> Yes.
The other question I have is in regards
to a traffic study and your um entrance
and exits to and from the development.
Um Duke Street, I go down there all the
time. I essentially could live in County
Park. I run those trails like hundreds
of times a week. Um and there has been
multiple occasions where I have either
almost been hit by a car. I can't get
out of where I'm coming from. So, I am
not particularly pulling in and out of
Sunnyside, but I'm very familiar with
the um you know, safety of that street
and particularly at certain times of
day. Um the traffic is a is a lot
busier. Now, you're going to add let's
say 80 homes rounded up with two cars
each. That's 160 cars going in and out
of this site potentially um with the um
current traffic conditions that were
already closed on Duke Street. So, I'd
just like to know a little bit what
you're doing as far as safety measures
to ensure that um traffic is um entering
and exiting that particular property
safely. Um and any thoughts on like
maybe innovative would you do one way in
one way out like how would you handle
that?
>> I'll start this and if you want to tag
along
we so we had a um we had an engineer a
traffic engineer look at the project and
determined that the project is exempt
from needing to have a traffic study
done based on the ordinance.
There's that. We do not we do not know
to date if we need to. I think we are
going to have to go to the traffic
commission
um as part of this process. So that is
you know to be determined how that will
go but we absolutely will be in front of
them as it pertains to the real nuts and
bolts of it. Um,
again based on
where things are at, we don't have
direct connection to Duke Street. It is
not a city street. It's a pendot road.
Um, we we absolutely agree with you. It
is a global issue, not a, you know,
Sunnyside or Sycamore Ridge issue. And
we will absolutely do anything in our
power to work towards making that
better. But I want to very clear that
like we don't really see having much
direct correlation
with our plan. We we have not we have at
least not been um made aware of those.
>> Um
>> yes.
>> So just my um friends on the city
themselves um from the traffic study
perspective because their engineer
suggested that it wouldn't be necessary.
I that a little bit hard to believe
based off of other plans that we have
discussed in previous meetings. Um, so
is that a factual thing or will they
actually need a traffic study?
What they did was they conducted a trip
generation
and the trip generation then triggers
whether or not there is um a study
needed. And so according to their trip
generation a study is not needed.
So according to how they they conducted
their drip generation
um and then can you go into a little bit
more about the challenges um that the I
just want to understand um if I recall
the words correctly it was said that the
public's works capacity for that
development only was would only allow
for 79 homes
and to have a maximum of 79 homes on
that site, correct? Or you have you have
your 79 homes. Um
why?
So that's important because um there's a
maximum and so what that means is
um there can be no future development on
Sunnyside. So um if another resident
wanted to um do an addition um add any
type of capacity they would not be able
to because they would have maxed out the
amount of the of the usage
>> is that
>> they would have capacity
>> specific to the Sycamore Ridge land. It
wouldn't would that affect
>> it's because of their it's because of
their density. It's because of it being
79 houses. Now, we have spoken with the
applicant about that who has um talked
about offering
um residences. This is all based on um
number of bedrooms.
And so what the applicant has proposed
is um offering more residences that have
less bedrooms because that will make the
it will make the number less. And so as
you do the as you do the calculation,
the more bedrooms you have, the more
sewer capacity you need. Um, and so you
can you can play with it by having um
less bedrooms, but the point remains
that
they would they would ultimately max out
um the sewer usage. So there would be
like zero room for development
on the whole peninsula.
>> No, on the I'm sorry, on the the
southern end of the peninsula.
>> Are you um are you sure about that?
Because that's not the way we
interpreted it. In fact, during our due
diligence period, we were um we got a
letter saying that there was 116 units
available and um and it was when we
received our you want to speak to it.
>> Yeah. When we hold on for one second.
When we received our uh willingness to
serve. It literally is what it sounds
like. It's the willingness to serve
letter. So, we have permission to use
27,500
gallons per day sewer capacity. Um I
don't I what I don't understand or what
I don't know is this is new information
to me that that we're taking up all of
that. Second reason why it's a little
bit confusing and unnerving is that by
And by right, every lot
is taken in consideration with sewer
capacity. So when we go in for a
development, it's in addition to every
lot whether it's hooked up or not. So I
do not agree with the ruling that
there's no more sewer capacity. If there
is a lot in in Sunnyside, you should be
able to build on that lot by right and
hook up to public water and public
sewer.
>> Right. But you also might have to you
might have to
You might have to um tap in.
>> You absolutely will have to tap in. But
that is is already calculated. What
they're allowing for is an addition to
what's already on the peninsula, not
saying this is the peninsula's capacity.
That was my understanding.
Um I have one one final question. I'll
um in the world that I live in things
are scheduled by um percentage of
completion.
Um it's been said that the city has
shared some concerns regarding the of um
certain details that are missing from
this uh plan. So I would like just
curious to know um what do you think the
percentage of completion is from for
your tenative plan and what do you think
the realistic milestones are from the
city to get that to a state that um the
city would feel more comfortable
considering to move this project
forward.
Um and then um in regards to that um
with the followup meetings that were had
after the letter was received um
regarding some of those details of that
need to be addressed. Um how was those
communications? How was that was you
know are you in agreement with the
things that are in that letter? Are you
disagreeing with the things that are in
that letter? And then you know I'll take
a pause there.
Um, thank you, Commissioner Super. Um,
so I think uh it's it's a let me start
by saying um the preliminary plan, final
plan process that is set up in Miss Aldo
and I would even say maybe even in the
state code um does not provide for um a
lot of difference between these two. In
other words, Preliminary plans are often
expected to have a similar level of
engineering unless the municipality
allows otherwise as the final plan. And
that is part of what I think we're up
against and having a tenative plan
before you where we're trying to get buy
in on uh I think a good concept and
trying to be uh very you know honest
about what we're trying to do and also
acknowledge that there's additional
engineering that has to be done. Um so I
think that that is one of the um
important issues to note here. So as to
the percentage complete from you know to
the point where we would be
constructing.
Um you know I of course I did this kind
of work for a long time and I'd say you
know we're probably somewhere hovering
around the the 60% mark and that's
because there's a lot that is often um
not even uh always in the public eye or
even in the commission's perview as to
what happens even after the plan uh is
conditionally approved here. There's
often a very long list of agreements
that lawyers start to work on and
there's a lot of technical comments that
have to be done. We would have to write
the HOA for the planning commission. The
ordinance allows us to actually do that
after approval but before recordation.
Um all the signatures have to be
gathered and uh the bond needs to be
posted and I could go on and on. And so
all of that does take a significant
amount of time to accomplish. So, I
don't want to short change um all of the
work that even has to happen after a
conditional approval is is given by the
commission.
>> You had a second part to your question.
>> Curious to know if you are um in
agreement with providing the necessary
details that the city is requesting for
the letter that was dated September 8,
2025.
I'll I'll let the owner speak to that
more directly, but I'll just say um that
uh I you know I reviewed the letter
myself and I think as Joe said these are
all issues that can be addressed and
where there's a will there's a way and I
wasn't uh personally um you know very
surprised by any of the comments and I
think that we were expecting a lot of
them and uh we know that there there's
more work to be done. Um so yeah Joe and
Mark do either of you want to elaborate
on that?
quick comment. Um, gentlemen right here,
front right here. Um,
um, no, you're good. Um, I would just I
just have an encouragement. Uh, just
kind of going back to what Commissioner
Nicole said about the affordability of
your housing.
Um, by all means, if you have a target
resident that you're looking to be in
these residents, I would encourage you
to to mention that because if you take
the word affordable and you place it
beside HOA,
HOA all but disqualifies affordable.
So, I would just encourage you moving
forward if you are saying that or if
you're desiring to have a target
resident to say that because it's like a
sh my head moment when I hear you say
it's affordable,
but on one of your slides it says
$386,000 starting point. So, I don't
know what world you live in, but
$386,000
starting to move into a home, it's not
affordable for a whole bunch of people.
You guys are really smart men.
Otherwise, you would have came up with
this plan. So, um just think about that.
Chew that up a little bit and think on
that. That's all.
>> Thank you.
Um, Mr. Weeks, if I may just provide one
quick followup, and this is actually for
the broader commission and the room as
well, but I I just wanted to um make
note of the HOA issue because I know
that that word has some connotation to
it about what that what comes along with
that. And um the the
HOAs have become increasingly common and
uh to be frank part of that is is also
driven by our storm water ordinance. Uh
what often happens is there's one
facility to serve multiple properties or
multiple houses and uh out of
affordability for the development
there's usually a central facility that
then all of these individual houses
become responsible for and there has to
be some entity that governs that. if
these are for sale homes. Um, and a
perfect example of this is actually the
affordable homes that are on Chesapeake
Street that Saka built. That whole
neighborhood there is a part of an HOA
and there's a storm water facility at
the bottom of it that all of them have
to maintain including the parking lot.
And the more infrastructure that comes
along in these projects, the more
expensive those HOA fees become. And I
think one of the commendable things
about this project is uh Mark and Joe
and and the designers involved are
trying to take a hard look at the amount
of infrastructure that they're providing
in this project. And that is the only
reason Mark is able to quote a number as
low as he just did because I've never
even heard of an HO quite that low
before. So I think that this team is is
truly working to try to make this a
project where there's low maintenance
and that requires the repairing buffers
to serve as the storm water and that
requires it us to think creatively about
how the roads are uh and curbs and
sidewalks and and all the rest.
>> By no means am I trying to imply
anything. These gentlemen have been
super transparent with everything you
said to this point. I appreciate that.
However, I will say I said what I said.
>> Totally knows. Thank you, Mr.
>> One last question. Uh be brief so that
the way we can hear from the public. Um
there's water all around this plane and
I know you have a flood plate in it goes
within the flood plane limits, but I'm
thinking climate change that water is
rising. Seven years ago, we had that
river was just overflooding its banks.
Can these structures um
can they uh sustain sustain some of this
damage even minimal flooding? And will
these uh if I have a mortgage on this on
some of these problems, will I have to
buy I'm sure buy flood insurance which
will add to that.
>> Yeah, that's a great question. Um
in Sycamore Ridge, we are uh that's
probably the one of the of nicer things
about the site. It is very high in
elevation compared to the flood plane.
Um so, you know, we're taking our
lickings on steep slopes and complexity
in the site, but that is certainly one
thing that we don't have to deal with.
Uh we're nowhere near the flood plane.
Um the we are utilizing
property that we own in a flood plane or
around a flood plane.
specifically for repairing buffer
installation and part of our storm water
but no housing be anywhere near it.
May I ask a question?
One of the things I was looking at in
the audience, of course, we have many
members of the audience who were here
back in 2014
when the planning commission approved
essentially a ninepage
document of modifications that needed to
be done for the tenative plan to go
through and that was for 300 units. I'm
just wondering with considering the
history of that, what will make this
different? Are we looking
12 pages. Obviously, a lot has happened
in 11 years.
Yeah, that that is the crux of the
issue. I mean, I spoke I spoke to this
this is a really high level thing, but
um we we really we really would love
staff to consider
um looking at this differently. The
comprehensive plan while it's not the
eco district concept is not embedded in
our ordinance.
Um
we are having to kind of create the
airplane while we're flying. Okay, it is
not there are no ordinances for what we
are doing. There's engineering again,
there's engineering standards and
there's engineering best practices and
building codes and the al like and
there's a lot of ordinances that are in
the city um that are close,
but that is our question like do we
really need to have nine pages of
waivers that you that you y'all need to
call through or Can we have our engineer
talk to your engineer and and see that
it is satisfactory
from a again from an engineering
standpoint
meets code those types of things and
with an understanding like yeah Joe this
is actually not meeting ordinance but we
support and we verify that this road's
good. We support and verify that this
storm water plan's good. We verify and
support your design layout is good. That
is what we would really really
appreciate from the planning staff
moving forward.
>> Can you help me understand why we should
allow you to negotiate through certain
processes and procedures when we do not
let anybody else do that?
>> I don't don't necessarily think so. Um I
think it's more of
A I think it's a more of an
understanding of intent. Um I don't I'm
not asking an engineer to give way or
undermine
a design. I am asking for um
intent to be appreciated like it like
again like the last project was the last
project was in the same place. I just so
happened again because of foresight and
thoughtfulness. I did not have to
put in curbs like that technically was a
waiver probably. I did not have to
install
sidewalks. That was probably a waiver.
I did not have to do a lot of things
over there
because it doesn't make any sense to do
that. There's not a single sidewalk or
curb in Sunnyside right now.
And so we're trying again to do this
thing and I get it. Um, you want the
city ordinance is designed to produce
streets that look like King Street, look
like Chestnut Street, not Sunnystein,
not Davis.
>> With all due respect, sir, I think
you're running two issues together here.
There's a lot of flexibility in the
flexible residential development option.
That's why it's called that. You're
allowed to many things that are
otherwise required in the city. But the
the threshold issue that Miss Logan has
here is whether you have made a complete
submission that's meaningful enough so
that the city staff can meaningfully
review this and that this commission can
meaningfully act on it. And I I I with
all due respect I think they're separate
things, sir.
>> Yeah, I I understand. I I did not
not absorb the question properly. So in
that regard, I would just refer back to
what Douglas said. I think we're at 60%.
And I think that's all all inclusive of
every easement and legal document that
we have to sign.
>> And and what I'm saying is the 60%
I think it's it's I don't necessarily
have a question, but more of a
statement. Um you know, side area has a
long history of being shortsighted with
projects for for decades going going
back decades.
>> Um, similar to the community that that I
came out of. Um, we've been shortsighted
on many projects and and uh short
changed. So
we and and with the things that need to
be completed,
um it appears as though the community
just deserves more
um completion of these pro of these uh
of the things that you have to complete
um
because that's what they deserve. And I
I believe that um you know it's a
community that has integrity
and u wants to develop
and um and needs to have uh their best
interests in mind and and what shows
that is more completion and further
progress and not you know trying to
complete the
repair the plane.
as you're flying. That's I think that's
what you said. That what you said.
>> Yeah, it was a nice metaphor at the
time.
>> So, while you're flying, so um that's a
statement. Um and for the record.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. I I definitely might have more
questions after the public speaks. Um,
but before we move forward, I just want
to say like, you know, we're talking
about creativity here. And I don't think
this plan is very creative. I think that
this is a size down version of a
suburban development that we might see
outside of the city where you have
larger lots. These might not be McN
McMansions, but I know a chicken nugget
when I see it. You're talking about
equitable development and you're
providing units that are all seemingly
roughly the same size. So that means
that the people who are consuming that
only have one option in that
neighborhood. And to your point about
people and nature preserves, no pe if
you don't have people to enjoy it, it's
not a preserve. I don't necessarily
agree with that because it's a preserve.
However, to your point about people,
you're only offering this opportunity to
enjoy the environmental things you may
hope to provide to a certain type of
customer. So the lack of diversity of
housing types in this development is
greatly concerning. And I know I brought
that up last time.
>> I do not see great changes between your
original proposed plan and this proposed
plan. And I think that you could be
using the diversity of housing units to
not only provide different opportunities
for people to live here, whether it's
affordable or not, just different types
of family structures. You did mention
multigener generational housing. I have
great concerns that this type of housing
cannot provide that. As someone who has
lived in multigenerational housing, not
sure because they are rather small, it
seems from the plan. I don't have an
exact number on square footage, but I do
not find this current presentation
equitable. I do not find it creative,
and
I'm very upset between this presentation
and the one originally proposed.
>> I have a question for you, gentlemen. I
think we've had a very a lengthy but
very productive discussion. I think
we've had we've heard the views of a
number of the people here on the
commission as well as the views of the
city and the the next step is the
hearing continues. I will open this up
for public comment. There are people
here. Uh my question for you and if you
wish to consult privately about this is
that you wish to withdraw your
application or would you like to hear
public
That's that's that's your call folks.
It's your application.
>> We would like to hear the public
comments.
>> Okay. Very well. Uh this is now the time
for public comment. The applicant has
made their statement. Made it statement.
Count commission has asked its
questions. Whoever would like to be
heard for public comment, please raise
your hand. And what I'll ask you to do
is uh Yes. And please uh you like us up
at the microphone? Yes. We'll ask
Whoever wants to comment to come up to
the microphone and we'll have you sworn
in by the court reporter and then you
may make your statement on the record.
And I've seen you raise your hand right
there. I'll give you the first privilege
like heard first. Yes.
We are not a 350,000
community.
We are far from that.
Apparently
going to take them home. Do you prepared
to Mount Greta?
Dude, you're a beast.
You're a beast. Mount Greta is an art
community. They do art shows up there
every year.
People go to the shop.
They have the theater.
We don't have that.
your two houses that you built down back
of us was in a flood plane. To this day,
no one knows how you got the okay to
build in a flood plane because the house
that the second one to the left, there
was a little lean tube built there and
the city raised hell about that.
So, how you got to building the flood
plane? You somebody's pocket and that's
all this is about. You making billions
while we live there. We like our little
community.
We don't want to be part of the city
where you have all the rich people doing
what they're doing.
That's not what we're about.
And you said about an environmental
building. We got one right across the
road.
in the county park and it has a library.
Why do we need that? We don't.
We want to go to the park, we go across
the street.
We don't need it.
And it's not welcome.
And I think a lot of them, I know we all
live among each other, but
we don't want it.
the ground that you're trying to build
on was a junkyard.
Transmission, oil, diesel, gasoline,
power steering, fluid, all went into
that ground. And you say there's only
some
decades,
>> decades,
>> you've been there. I've been there.
>> Decades. And it's
down into the ground and you can't
convince me that there's only
>> It's ridiculous.
We're not a 300 50 80,000
community and you want to bring that
ain't going to go.
We're not coming up there.
So I like I like your one comment that
you made. Affordable
people can't afford to live in Lancaster
cities. That's why our homeless rate has
going skyrocket. Our seniors have to
choose between paying their bills or
taking their medication,
not going to a doctor's appointment.
350,000 ain't affordable.
100,000 isn't affordable.
65 85.
Bring your prices down there.
Build buildings like they did on South
Duke Street. Concrete building,
not some luxurious building. Build
buildings like that. That's affordable.
Like I said,
That's not even close to that right now.
That's the time that you want to build.
>> Thank you for your comments and uh in
light of the large number of people here
uh if you make keep your comments brief
that would be appreciated sir. Yes.
You're next.
>> Good evening.
I do. Dwayne Brenamman B re- m
Good evening. I'm a longtime member of
Sunnyside Menite Church and I currently
serve as our church board chair. So my
comments tonight are on behalf of the
church. So while there's there's
certainly some excitement for us as a
church thinking about having new
neighbors, we also have some significant
concerns with this plan. And there's one
in particular that I want to draw your
attention to this evening. As presented,
the plan would have a significant
negative impact on Sunnyside Menite
Church. Specifically, this plan would
reduce substantially our occupancy
because it would eliminate, by my
estimation, about 23 of our existing 48
parking spaces.
The church's site plan that was approved
in 1996
has these 48 parking spaces on it.
Per city zoning ordinance with 48
spaces. We can have 192 people in our
building. That's based on four occupants
per space. Practically speaking, four
people don't come in the car. So in
reality, our occupancy is probably a lot
lower than that. one or two people in
the car. So our concern as a church is
we need to maintain our current number
of parking spaces which allows us to
maintain our occupancy and continue to
function as church. So if this tenative
plan moves forward, the question for the
city is how will the city ensure the
church maintains our current number of
parking spaces?
Can I have your name again, sir?
>> John.
I live out. I was born and raised.
I worked at the 25 years.
I know what
is up there and I know Sunny
and I would love to see Sunnyside grow
but not the way they want to grow.
Like she said, affordable housing.
bring people in to build a nice little
house. Why do you need a live?
We lived in a
little shack when we moved to where my
brother house.
Yes, we were
the city. We were always down.
But you know what?
There were 200 homes out there and we
knew everybody.
Now where can you go in this city that
we were a small
community?
Now you want to bring in something this
big.
It's not going to fit. I would love to
see yes small a
live
street my son the house there
like she said yes I see traffic up and
down that street every day
up
and you want to put all this back in
there
There's going to be all the time people
do not do 35 miles hour
by the time you're
street
back
Thank you.
>> Yes.
Yes.
MC capital C L U C A S
as a resident of Sunnyside.
I would like some clarification on this.
If he builds 79
buildings and we're not able to build
anymore,
are we as residents going to be
informed? Um because because I have
another property out there and
eventually he would like to do something
with. Um, and if he puts 79 units in,
which you know,
is it going to limit what I can do on
that other property? Okay, the church
has what, three vacant lots. Is that
going to limit what they can do on their
lives? Um, you know, so that is a
concern that I'm having at the moment.
um and knowledge. You know, nobody
really seems to know for sure if he does
79 if we can't do anything else. So,
that does need some clarification on our
resident end. Um maybe somebody wants to
build on and they can't. You know, as
families grow, you know, some of your
families are parents, grandparents, and
kids sometimes now because they can't
afford to have a living arrangement all
of their own. Okay. So, if they have to
build on but they can't, that presents a
problem in the community as well. That's
my concern. And being informed is the
number one thing with that.
Mr. Albert, if I could just um we did uh
I did find the copy of the suits
capacity verification request. I'm happy
to read it out loud.
>> I'm sure that would be appreciated.
>> It's dated um September 2nd and was sent
to uh Jaclyn P. Holland at Mac
Engineering, which is the applicant's
engineer, and it's um a sewage capacity
verification request. The city has
completed our review of your sanitary
sewage capacity verification request
dated August 10th, 2025 for the proposed
development project on the Sunnyside
Peninsula. Upon review, the city finds
we have sufficient sanitary sewer
capacity for projected daily flow of
27,500
gallons per day, but not the requested
2800,000 gallons per day. The generated
flows would be conveyed through the
city's Sunnyside and Stevens Avenue
sewage pumping stations with final
sewage treatment taking place at the
north treatment train of the city's
wastewater treatment plant. As of the
date of this letter, no sanitary sewer
hydraulic overloads exist or projected
within 5 years for these city
facilities. If the full 28,000 28,000 GB
is desired, the Sunnyside sewage pump
station would need capacity increased at
the developer's expense. All
Pennsylvania Department of Environmental
Protection SE sewage facility planning
approval should be obtained as required.
No below grade basement gravity sewage
facilities shall be connected to the
city sewer system. Below grade basement
gravity facilities are defined as
fixtures with open sewer connections,
sinks, toilets, toilets, drains, washing
machine connections, etc. located below
the surface elevation of the city's
upstream sewer line manhole cover for
which the owner's private sewer lateral
connects. And then it concludes with his
um contact information. That's from
Brian Hartner from the city of
Lancaster.
>> Okay. So, you're saying that the city
said there was sewer capacity for 27,500
gallons, but there was another number
that was requested. 28,000 gallons were
was requested. So five um 500 gallons
per day difference from what was
requested.
>> Um
but that I don't does that answer the I
don't think that answers the question of
Mr. Lucas about what that just says like
this development can have 275. So there
would only be 500 gallons per day
capacity left for
>> for what?
>> For the um
the north treatment train of the
wastewater treatment plant
>> and that's the plant that services the
Sunnyside area.
>> Correct.
>> So I'm sorry. Can you just um cl clarify
how that would affect the other
residents who are currently living in
Sunnyside? And just let's use um I don't
recall her name, but this is the lady's
example. Um she has another property on
site if she would want to build
something on that site. Would she be
limited in what she could do because of
what these gentlemen are proposing to
do?
>> Sorry. Potentially she could be limited.
There's only 500 gallons per day left
remaining on the site. So, how that's
distributed is based on the number of
bedrooms. Um, any other projects that
are proposed. Um, I don't know the exact
numbers of how many gallons per day you
need per bedroom.
>> Thank Thank you for bringing that to our
attention. Okay. Who would like to be
heard next?
Yes, sir.
I I excuse me. Uh Clifford, right?
Um, I was listening to the plans. I
think Joe's he's really taking a beating
here on this because I remember when we
were sitting in that same seat looking
for approval for so we Katherine Black
can put her place in and we went through
pure hell to do that. And u I feel for
the guy. I think this plan may need some
adjustment there. But also there's a lot
of sore laterals in Sunnyside that's not
even being used because I think uh back
in 1984
they well sewers went in like 85 I think
something like that. So I think like
they took 200 houses out of there over
100 houses that were removed from
Sunnyside because the landlords didn't
want to put the money into the houses to
meet city code. So there is a lot of
laterals out there that are not being
used.
Now I know there's a lot of people that
are not in favor with with Joe's plan.
Myself I could not afford that. But we
can't grow
with you know in order to grow you have
to have an open mind with things. Yeah.
You need adjustment. There's a lot of
people, even my friends, that are not
happy with it. I get that. But at the
same time, what if it was your plan and
you're trying to do this? You know,
I just I just think it's unfair for Joe
to get beat up the way he did. Um, and
uh, he's got some work to do. I agree.
But I don't see it as a total wipeout.
I'm sorry. Sunnyside could use
improvement. Maybe not 300 some thousand
dollar houses, but that's an expensive
project. Do you buy the land, the all
the the fees involved, lawyers,
engineers, permits, plum, you know, it's
a lot. How do you get your money back?
You know, those houses were $100,000 or
$150,000 a piece. He'd never get the
money back. His children's grandchildren
would reap the benefits from that
project.
So, you know, he might have to adjust
his prices. I agree. But in order to do
something like that, it takes money. And
that's why the city never developed in
Sunnyside because it wasn't feasible for
them because they didn't see no way. How
can you build lowincome houses?
There's no money there. There's no money
to be made.
So, I I think Joe needs a little bit of
relief here. I'm sorry community. I live
out there. I know you people. But I do
uh believe in expanding. I believe in
growth.
And like I said, I look at him as if
what if that was me? What if I wanted to
do something, you know? Wow. Yeah. I
mean, but there has to be a change in
Sunnyside,
you know. Maybe this is it, maybe not.
But um I just want the panel and and my
neighbors
to give the guy a chance, you know, and
and maybe help him instead of condoning
the project. Give him some ideas, some
input. Hey Joe, you know what about
this? What about that? How can that help
help us? How can we help you Joe? you
know. So,
so that's but Bernie, I'm just saying I
remember Bernie I remember when Eddie
had to go for permission to put the
place in you're living in now. It's the
same thing Bernie. He didn't have
anybody.
>> Excuse me. This is Well, I'm just saying
>> this is not what this is about is by
play back and forth with the audience.
>> Right. Right. I'm sorry, but I'm I'm
just saying I we've all been here
before. Anybody that wants to put
something in out there, we've all been
here before for zoning to do that. And
we had to go through the same thing
Joe's going through. His plans is
bigger. That's all. But I'm saying, you
know, when K when we had put signs up
for zoning for her her place to go in, I
was worried to death, man, who's going
to show up and oppose against it, you
know, and what am I going to say to to
to defend her in her defense,
you know, and we did have lots of
problems. They didn't want her house out
there. It's too big. It's too beautiful.
They didn't want it, but we got it. We
It fought. But thank God for Mayor
Smith, Charlie Smith. He stood up for
her and said it's going to happen. But
I'm just saying, and now it's, you know,
it's beautiful. It's right in there.
I'm just saying give the man a chance.
That's how I am. I'm a fair guy. Whether
you like it or not, I'm fair. And I
think everybody deserves a fair chance,
a fair shake in something like this. or
whether you're putting a single home in
a trailer or anything. And I I don't
understand the sewer the sewage because
there's a lot of units taken out. So
there's a lot of stuff that's not being
used in this city for that.
And I think guy I think they need to re
relook at that. I honestly do because
>> thanks man.
>> Exactly. I know that
>> f folks, we're not we're not having
conversations among
>> we're not having conversations among the
audience. We're here for testimony,
>> right? Uh, you know, I'm just saying
that I just think the man deserves a
fair chance. That's all I'm saying.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Okay.
>> I would just like to say that we will
follow up with um the
Brian Herner who is in charge of the the
sewer capacity. We'll of course follow
up with him. I also wanted to just add
that there some of this confusion over
sewer capacity. If you remember, the
plan was originally um projected to be
65 to 70 units. We also at the time were
not um confirmed on the um what was
being proposed on the north end of
Sunnyside with the environmental center.
And so all of these numbers have have
really only recently been calculated.
And so going back to that, um Brian did
also provide um how he conducted the um
the estimate. And so he specifically
said that in terms of the sewer capacity
request, due to the tight constraints of
utilizing the existing pump station's
capacity, he requested the detailed
proposal
and he contain the number of existing
parcels. This is all of Sunnyside. The
number of existing parcels, new parcels,
new housing units where sewer capacity
is requested.
And so that's where and that's where it
goes on to state that um vacant lot
parcels still count as new EDU
connections to the sewer system. Um the
city it goes on to talk about how many
um units are used. So 350 three or four
bedroom 300 GDP for GPD for a twobedroom
and 250 GPD for onebedroom and so that's
again going back to using the bedrooms
as the the capacity so um and that did
include
all of the unit that when you do the
proposal that's how it how it's done
again I will reach back out to Brian
Harner I've actually already emailed him
to make sure that we can get
clarification on this point I do not
want to
Um, but I I just do want to send that up
as a warning flag. I was also advised
that I should get sworn
>> I do.
>> Um, are we allowed to respond to
resident comments?
>> Absolutely.
>> Okay. So, I I just want to respond to
that comment u about like the open mind.
Um,
you know, I wouldn't be so upset if I
was looking at a plan that had a
diversity of housing types. That was one
of my big grievances with the sketch
plan initially proposed to us. And
everything we're seeing is a
monoculture. So that that note about
open mind does go both ways because we
did offer comments to the developers as
it relates to this project that we're
not seeing put into this plan. On top of
that about process,
um you know it this is a slightly
different process than what a regular
homeowner has to go through. You have a
single individual lot. You're doing a
small project. You're not quite going
through a planned residential procedure.
You don't have a public hearing like
this. Like this is all a legal judicial
process. Um,
when it comes to this plan, I would be
more amendable to development like this,
if it were phased in smaller scales. You
were said like, "Hey, I'm going to build
10 units. This is phase one. I'm going
to build 10 units. Maybe that's your
storage units and some lots throughout
the development and you're planning for
future phases later on that incorporate
other housing styles." Like, this is
just all at once and it's all the same.
So, I can understand some like yeah, you
got to give people a fair shake. You
don't want to beat on them too much, but
this isn't the first time they've been
here. And from my perspective that
there's not an open mind about the types
of things we can see on the site. That's
how I feel up here.
>> May I speak to that?
>> Um, Mr. Dash, we uh definitely remember
the conversation from last time and I I
do appreciate that. Um, again reviewing
the YouTube video just refreshed me too.
Even at that meeting I think like
collectively
uh your group as well as our group kind
of landed at like this crossroads
that it's just not possible to do a lot
of different diversity. The number one
reason diversity doesn't actually work
here is like we I mean we're already
talking about the sewer capacity issue.
So diversity is gonna uh if we go up
we're going to have to I mean that's
going to increase the number of units
and we don't have the capacity to put
more units here. So what what you have
here is like flat residential homes
which I appreciate. They're on slabs and
You call it a monoculture and I you know
agree to disagree it is what it is but
uh we have absolutely looked at
diversifying
the the type of housing I think all the
past well not all but I don't I don't
know all past projects have have looked
at going going up and and and they're
all facing the same the same issue. It
is sewer sewer capacity and so we have
to do what we can with cards that were
dealt. I wish we could do that. Um the
other the other uh comment that was made
at the last meeting was we would have to
provide sprinkler systems. As soon as
you go up and you're basically building
multif family and that's a entirely
different uh set of rules and processes.
We would need parking lots and dumpsters
and all kinds of things. Um it's a whole
different category in and of itself. So
I again then and also now
We have waited. It's not like we're
avoiding or we're ignoring. We're
absolutely hearing you. It's just not
possible here. Like literally, this is
the best we can do.
>> That's the thing that blows my mind
because the eco district, while we don't
have ordinances drafted out in pool, it
does specify lot coverage. And so to the
point of fulfilling the goals of the eco
district, going up reduces your lot
coverage, which also goes in line with
having more ecological diversity in the
area. I'm not a code expert, but I do
think fourplexes might be able to have
uh structures with no sprinklers. I
could be wrong about that.
>> As soon as you hit three,
>> three,
>> so that's again duplex.
>> Triplex, you're instantly multif family.
>> You are no longer residential building
code.
>> But even the sizing of your units, you
have units that are all the same size.
>> I mean, 12 to,800 square feet,
>> two and three bedrooms is not the same
size. Do you have a listing of how many
different sized units are offered?
Because just from the plans here and
like maybe there's more detail, but
looking at these plans, they all look
approximately the same size.
>> So, we did that very strategically. So,
this is representing a footprint. That
footprint, if you look very very
closely, it includes even portions of
the garage and the uh the private
outdoor living spaces that are also
required. Every home now has to is
required to provide 75 square feet of
private outdoor space. That footprint
we've strategically
laid the laid out the site to allow for
any home to go anywhere. So if again
that is directly trying to get more
diversity. If we said, "Oh, we can only
put this specific twobedroom right here.
If no one buys it, that stinks.
that we did not want that. We wanted
ability for somebody to say, "Look, I
that's what I want or hey, we we want a
bigger house. Can we get that house
there?" Yes.
1,200 to 18 isn't a huge diversity of
range for me, especially when talking
about multigenerational
housing support. Depends on how big the
family is, of course, but three
generations can get pretty wide. Yeah.
Um
I I just don't The creativity has been
explored here. I don't know what your
proform looks like, but as I understand
it, you acquired the sites for in total
$650,000
roughly. Is that is that
>> Yes, sir.
>> Okay. Like you have a big site and a lot
of room to play. Like like I said
earlier, if you were just talking about
some units of housing, I would be way
more palatable to some of what's being
proposed. But you're just putting this
across the entire site and that's what
we can expect for the entire future of
side and that's that's concerning at
this point.
>> Gentlemen, can I can I jump in real
quick? Everything that everyone is
saying is valuable, but can I just
suggest that we keep the main thing the
main thing like what we're here to to
discuss. Can we do that because we're
not going to everything isn't going to
get solved in our own eyes tonight. So,
can we just keep the main thing in front
of us?
Yes, sir.
Morris.
I do
I'm here listening to this discussion
here and realizing that I look at these
gentlemen and believe they're proposing
something that's incredible. Doesn't to
say everything soft, but this is a heck
of a sight to try to do that with rock
former junkyard.
I came to this country in 1960.
Three months later, I'm running out to
Williamson Park, which is now the wean
hills up there. We finished by drinking
at
fountain.
We lay down and drank water. We didn't
carry bottles.
When I'm standing there, I'm seeing
people from Sunnyside hold their cars
with bottles on that they filled up to
take back across Duke Street to their
homes. There was no running water.
That was 1960.
1980 I find myself as mayor of city
served as city engineering public works.
We wanted to do something about
Sunnyside to help. So we put in water
30 years after they were promised. We
put in water.
We improved the streets. We had public
meetings at the Menite Church. We caught
some help at some of those meetings
because people didn't want to change.
But in general, they agreed it was
necessary. I know some of these people
did because we held town meetings in
Sunnyside. Sunnyside was something I
believed in
when
Quarry was threatening to close. They
wanted to fill the quarry up with water
without doing anything. We took them to
court actually through the zone here.
Made them do some reclamation. There's a
bench part of that so far above where
the water would fit. So if somebody fell
in in certain places, it would be cold.
Somebody needs to look at into that in
the future as you develop the site. But
I'm here to I don't suggest that all
these problems, many of them shouldn't
be looked at and resolved. I do think
there's a need to either say the city
say we want to make this happen and
we're going to work with you but you got
to meet certain requirements or you can
throw all kinds of obstacles. I'm not
saying you, I'm saying in general. And
you can decide not to do it. I wouldn't
want to take this risk. I think it's a
heck of a risk that they've put in
apparently 600 and some thousand
dollars. They've done two cottages. I've
been there. I've toured them. I've
looked at it.
I think they've done a heck of a job to
try to make them fit in. And no, you
can't. Listen, talk about affordable
housing. They have no government money
in this. No, nobody would do that. You
look at the developments downtown.
Market price is the right word. Most of
them are market price. Most of them
don't have affordable housing. If you're
HDC, you get millions of dollars so they
become affordable. To ask these
gentlemen to put affordable housing in,
yes, maybe title it right. I understand
that. But ask them to do affordable
housing. The money isn't there. You
can't do that. So, I appreciate you
listening to the citizens and to the
presentation and trying to work through
this. I hope there's to get there is
what I sincerely say because I think
again worry was operating it's not
anymore the junkyard was there there was
no water and sewer we've come a long way
and I simply said to side
be involved
try to be a little open
George M.
I'm here tonight. Um, I'm a friend of
Joe and a property owner on Sunnyside.
Um, I have to say, you know, we've been
through this before.
The site has its challenges, its past
and its present and probably will in the
future as well. There's a lot to take
into consideration here. I have to
commend these guys for their their
efforts, their fortitude and creativity,
the residents for speaking their mind
for and against this whichever way they
go and for all of you for the hard work
that you have. I have some questions.
Um, for all of you. Um, have we used
this uh flexible residential development
u application type for anything of this
scale before? It's it's new to me as a
planner. I know we've had it on the
books, but I feel like there's an
opportunity here both for creativity and
for some forward thinking to address a
place that we've had plans come before
us in the
that haven't worked out. Um to do
something that excuse me to do something
there is going to take a lot of forward
thinking. And I think this board and
others here in the city can work. These
gentlemen are here to work and listen to
the public and to you and to make
something happen. And I think that's an
important thing for Sunnyside seeing
that we've had you know the history of
what we've had there and challenges of
the site both
There's a lot to be done there. I hear
us talking about sewer. I think it's
important uh to address that. Obviously,
I mean, I think through the GPS that the
city has, you could probably figure out
exactly what the buildout would be based
on the zoning and figure out exactly how
many edus
and that equates to a number of gallons.
It's it's not insurmountable. You can
figure it out. Um, if the numbers need
to be adjusted a little bit, so be it.
But let's move forward with something
here. Um, I hear the gentleman from the
Menanite Church talking about losing
some parking spaces. I used to be a
planner for the county. I don't know
what plan he's referring to, but it's my
understanding that if you don't build
those things within five years, they
have to go back under review again. Is
that not the case? I'm just asking that
question. Um, and lastly, um, I was just
looking at an article from the last time
we were here with 350 homes. Um, and in
the article, a former planner for the
city of Lancaster is on record saying
that we could hold as many as 500 homes
on Sunny Side. I mean, how would we
possibly have had sewer for that? How
did we get as far as we did with a 350
home capacity development?
Did we have those same questions? I
would just like for you guys to continue
what you're doing, residents, continue
to be there, listen to what's happening
in your neighborhood, and for all of you
to continue the hard work you're doing.
I think, you know, we it's not easy to
move forward and do something positive.
And I think our our rules and
regulations that we have with our
zoning,
uh, you know, tend to make what we all
call sort of cookie cutter. And I think
this flexible residential development
might allow us to do something that's
different and maybe something better,
but we won't know unless we take the
time to do it. So, keep going.
Thanks, George.
H
I just have a few things
with I'm 71 years old and
our family
me
another resern
because that's how bad
And I think they need to do another
study about how it is going and
I drove out. It was hard to get out or
get in because
you had to watch or
stay safe.
Another issue I have I want to know
about um this is kind of off the wall
$350,000
homes which are not
my home
out there
in 1989
they could not
start
in the dog area. Is that going to affect
the found
coming down the hill? What would that do
to my house? Als
the trees and stuff because four years
ago we had a lot of wind trees came down
off that property and pulled the
electric out of my house and the fire
company had to come out here and
fire
out
and then be concerned about all the
trees and everything. issue
is whebody
around there
and
that ground is not
clean.
I'm no scientist or whatever
stupid
you know to make room for more cars that
wasn't
cars
and you know just ran out
into
them and with rain and stuff that went
deep not
area close to the top of the ground.
It's good idea to take soil off, but how
much are you
going to be safe? I wouldn't want to
have
no way
up there
and then
it's Great. I have stuff that
ground coverage where it holds the stuff
together. It grows natural in my backy.
And I know a couple years ago they
someone was allowed to hunt out there
and I got really upset because they
would
up on the hill behind my house and at
that time I had a dog that kept outside
and inside and I was always afraid he
was shooting
and it wouldn't hit the
house or my
attitude had with our area And it wasn't
only it was also cheetah land.
So this goes way back. It's not just
something new. You know my house is only
assessed at $46,000.
Now what does that look like against
$350,000?
And how many people living in that want
to own a house a first time house can a
$350,000.
I mean, that's unrealistic.
Not too many.
>> Okay. Ma'am, I I think that the issue of
fact that understood to me that
>> well, ma'am, we've heard from about
eight people who made that point already
and this there's other people there's
other cases waiting to be heard.
>> I thank you
>> and I thank you for letting me come.
>> Okay.
>> Thanks, Mr. Gray,
>> this meeting takes me back. I'll tell
you,
seems like old times.
I moved here in the early 70s. The first
time I heard of Sunnyside.
Yes, I do.
Richard
moved here in the early 70s. The first
time I heard of Sunnyside was in the
80s. It was actually controversial
whether the city should put water and
sewer in. The next time I got involved
with side was the youth intervention
center.
Many of us opposed that because we knew
it would screw up future develop
that whole peninsula. Unfortunately, the
county went ahead and did next when I
was mayor
community basis
wanted to put affordable housing.
seemed like another month 20 years ago.
Well, this changed now. Oh, now it's
storm water. We have to do this and we
can reduce this number over and over and
over and over and over until finally we
can't do it.
Subsidized housing really affordable
housing awful lot
isn't available to me. The only thing
I'd say to you is
don't be 20 years from now when people
say there was an opportunity to develop
sunny side
the city got this way. Try to work out
and there's a lot of problems that I sat
here and listen to it tonight. There's a
lot of matters that have to be resolved.
Don't cut it short. Go ahead work and
see what we can do. See what these guys
can do. of what you all think is
necessary.
Don't do another 20 years down.
What do we have now?
Juvenile reformatory
which shouldn't even be in the city
and an environmental center which would
be a nice addition to the city but it
doesn't solve one of our critical
problems. That's housing. No matter what
level of housing one final thing said,
no public money is proposed to be used
in developing this
as Mayor Art and I
look how much will produce tax revenue.
Somebody has to pay for the service this
weekend. And this I heard six700,000
in tax revenue.
That's how many policemen, firemen, how
many other personnel can be employed. So
I'd urge you don't mix it tonight. Just
work on it. Massage it. See if some of
these problems can be resolved. See how
important they are. If they can't, then
move on.
Mr. Okay, at this point we the
commission has heard a lot of testimony
about uh the uh traffic, about uh the
environment, about possible
contamination from the old junkyard use
uh and as well as preserving the
character of the area. Uh in light of
the hour, does anyone have something to
offer that has not been testified to
before?
Yes, sir.
You were already sworn in, so we'll hear
from you again.
>> Thank you. This is Dwayne Brenamman
again. I just want to clarify one point.
Um, one of the earlier gentlemen who
commented seemed to seemed to be
implying that our 1996 plans were never
followed through on. I just wanted to
clarify that the 48 parking spaces and
the 23 that I believe this plan would
cause us to lose was built and has been
used for at least 29 years. Okay. Thank
you, sir. Okay. Is there anyone else who
has anything new to add that hasn't been
covered already?
>> Okay. I'll take you at your word, sir.
Dean Ser, I'm the pastor at Sunnyside
Menanite. Joe Mark, thank you for your
work, the vision for the um for the
junkyard.
Um I have been there for 25 years as a
an attender. I have never met a person
there that was mean. Um it's a wonderful
community.
If you folks, and I'm speaking, if you
have never been to Sunnyside,
it is one of the most unique places in
Lancaster County. And we would invite
you, I will personally give you a tour,
a tour of the peninsula. Probably John
to help me to not
we would love to have you join us on a
Sunday morning.
number, visit us. Um, it will help you
understand
what they love about it and what Joe and
Mark are proposing. Um, it's just it's
it's different. And if you come on the
first Sunday of a month, we do a really
nice pot.
>> Okay.
>> Am I invited?
>> Is there anyone else who has anything
new?
Okay. At this point, we're ready to
close
the board.
>> I mean,
I just want to throw this out. I mean, I
think Mayor Gray does have a point and I
personally am open to hearing more
conversation about this site. I don't
know how it works, but I know the MPC
allows for like mediation options, and
I'm just throwing that out there because
I think there's a discussion to be had
about the site.
>> So, there there is an option for that.
And so, essentially what it would
require, it would enable um Joe to come
back with an amended tenative plan. Um
but in order to do that, he would just
be required to wave the deadlines for
the um
right now we're going to the flexible
residential development. So, we're on
these very specific deadlines, which is
why the time we have the time
constraints. And so if
if the applicant waves their the um the
deadlines and gives the city more time,
then they would be able to come back
with a tentative plan that addressed all
of they would have to address all of the
um the notes that they have received
that have already been documented.
So I want to um just make a point here
that I think what you gentlemen are
doing is commendable. Um I think that
you have a big giant challenge in front
of you. You went from the little leagues
with your two cabins to the big leagues
now. Um and I also would um say to the
residents of Sunnyside Peninsula that
change is always scary. It definitely
is. Um it's not always welcomed. Um but
in nine times out of 10 change is
actually a good thing. Um, so tonight I
think that we're here a clarification
for maybe me personally is to determine
whether the current submission package
requires the necessary details that the
city needs in order to make an educated
decision or if we can
if it let's say it does not include
that. Do we have the ability to work
with the applicants
to to those goals.
It would be amazing to see something at
Sunnyside happen. I question whether
this is the correct plan. Um I trust the
team that is working on it. I think that
they have the best interest of the
community in mind. Um but I have major
concerns regarding the missing details
that the city still needs in order for
everybody to make an entire
um decision to on how to proceed with
this particular application.
>> So, may I ask is now a good time for us
to recess to discuss what our options
are?
>> I
that that is certainly appropriate.
>> Okay.
>> Well, can you just restate the opposite
stated earlier?
>> Yes. Yes. Uh for for the record, uh the
options got a little bit
because the applicant withdrew his
request for immediate final plan
approval. The options are either for the
city to grant preliminary plan approval
or or to continue the case for the
testimony or to make a determination to
reject the application that simples
in the application. So,
Well, the other thing is uh you could
continue the case for a hearing within
the time frames.
That's that's those are the options. Uh
summarize, we uh you know dismiss the
application as being complete. Uh you
continue the case to another for another
date for another hearing within the time
frame. Or you could preliminary
All these things worked out those
>> tenative plan approval.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Albert, um I just want to say on
behalf of the team here that um the
project team is open to extending the
timeline to help address some of the
comments that the city has raised. So I
um Miss Finn had mentioned earlier that
if the developer voluntarily chooses to
extend that timeline that uh that would
allow us additional time in which we
could address the comments and come back
with a tenative plan that does that that
addresses the comments and is amended.
So just wanted to make the commission
and you aware of that.
>> Well I appreciate the clarification but
the problem I have is that if the city
commences it preliminary plan app
process then that that triggers the
stays about enactment of any other
ordinance and things get frozen and I I
am opposed to the commission
the hands of the city being tied uh why
preliminary plan would be under approval
for an indefinite period of time that's
why we ask for a complete submission so
these things can be handled in an
expeditious fashion
city have any comment on this
>> I I have a question regarding um the
submission process. In the event tonight
that we would reject their application,
would they have the same ability to then
go through continue the partnership with
the city to go through the um
recommended changes and the comments
that the city is suggesting um pull the
necessary details together and then come
back or
>> absolutely and that's something I I want
to emphasize is that if the application
is dismissed as simply being incomplete,
the city the commission reached the
merits of the case in any way. We're
just saying there's just holes in it.
We're not saying it's a good or bad
application. We're not saying there
aren't a lot of good ideas. We're just
saying it's incomplete. There's not
enough information for us to act on
prejudice.
So,
we have a motion on the floor.
>> There's been no motion at this point.
Okay. Simply I simply stated the hearing
officer that testimony is closed and
it's ready for commission to do
something.
>> I I would like to move to go to
executive Um
>> section
board is going to take an executive
session. We'll try to keep it as brief
as possible, but there have been a lot
of points of view heard here and I think
respect there's some hiring out here.
Excuse us.
We're looking at this plan on on both
sides, you know, developers and also the
uh community. And uh we know that they
deserve the best and uh we we plan to
respect that.
Point of clarification, Mr. Albert and
Mr. Chairman. Um, does the rejection
mean that an entirely new application
needs to be filed or just that we come
back to the commission with a revision
of, you know, materials?
>> We need a a new application. It can be
based upon the existing materials, okay?
But it will need to be supplemented in
terms of the deficiencies the city
identified.
>> Okay? So, the application as submitted
is is dead as of now with the vote and a
new application would need to be filed.
>> Yes. Yes. Okay. Yes, that is correct.
>> Um, I'll just pass the mic here in case
uh the two owners here would like to ask
any questions about that.
>> Gentlemen, we just like to encourage you
to continue to work through this
project. Um, that there's a lot of gaps,
there's a lot of holes, there's a lot of
missing information uh that's necessary
in order for this project to continue.
So, I know that we just burst a bubble
right now. Um, but you can fill the
balloon back up later as you continue to
work through this process. So, best of
luck to you and thank you so much for
your time, your talent, your creativity.
We hope to see you back again.
>> Thank you.
that the hearing is concluded. I will
turn this matter back over chairman for
the remainder of Thank you.
Number three,
approval of the
meeting minutes for September the 3rd,
2025.
I have a motion on the floor.
Mr. Chair, I will make a motion to
approve the minutes from our previous
meeting of September 3rd, 2025.
>> I'll second
We have a motion on the floor uh for the
approval of the minutes September the
3rd, 2025.
Uh ready for the question.
All in favor, let it known by saying I
>> I
>> opposed. Eyes have it. Motion carry.
>> I'm sorry. Can you tell me again who
>> Andrew and then who was the second?
>> Okay.
>> And who can you just again also because
it was just hard for me to hear over
everything. Who made the motion?
Um
>> Okay.
>> No, I have that
>> from the solicitor. clarification from
the solicitor and then I added that.
>> Um, do you have your did I don't know if
by any chance you had written down what
you
>> I did
>> um because I'll just need that wording
for the minutes.
>> May I say it now?
>> Yes,
>> Mr. Chairman. I will make a motion to
reject without prejudice the plan as we
have before us this evening.
>> Okay.
>> And then the clarification was Help
me out.
Due to in application,
do you have to say which will require a
new application or not? No.
>> I appreciate that. Thank you. It was
just hard for me to hear everything.
>> Okay.
Moving forward, Mr. Chairman.
Number four, the subdivision and land
development
a uh 523 Woodward Avenue preliminary
final land development
conditional approval.
I just also um would like to interject
here that this is a um former Rackle
property. Um the
um the property contract with Rackle uh
just expired and so the um city is
taking this property over again um and
they're going to go through the process
of condemnation
and eminent domain for this property.
However,
your job as the planning commission is
to evaluate the plan on its technical
merits. So, it is going forward
regardless. And so, your it is your job
as the planning commission to determine
whether it is a viable plan and provide
your decision as such. So, your decision
is the same. It's, you know, conditional
approval, denial, but that's not I'm
telling you this for your information
regarding the owner, but it does not
need to impact your decision
and Kyle will tell you
the mic.
Okay.
Thank you, Chairman. Polite, members of
uh the commission, Dr. Finn, members of
the public. Uh my name is Kyle Postale
here from Towns Square Engineering,
representing the property owner, which
is Woodward Street LLC, represented
tonight by Mr. Uho Hume behind me. Uh
we're discussing 523 Woodward Street. Uh
this property uh highlighted there um
with frontage on both Woodward Street
and White alley, a public alley.
Uh the existing property has one single
family semi- detached home or an end
unit of a row home. Uh and the rest is
uh totally empty uh just grass and and
such. Uh the existing home, as Dr. Finn
mentioned, is being renovated as part of
a the rackle process.
But
the proposed subdivision of this.142
acre property uh will create two new
properties, thus bringing this lot to
three lots. Uh and the proposal is to
add on two new units uh onto that
existing end unit, thus creating a new
single family attached unit and semi-
detached unit. Um both of the all three
units uh both the existing and the two
uh proposed uh would then have uh paved
parking spaces, one for each accessible
from the alley. Uh a small sidewalk
going up to the back of the house.
Um they will both be connected with new
water and sewer laterals, one for each
property.
Um these are proposed to be fe simple
lots.
Uh I'll now discuss the other site
features.
Regarding storm water management, uh it
is handled on each property separately.
Um so you will see highlighted here a
small storm water infiltration trench
beneath uh the parking area and some
grass area of the backyards of each
unit.
And uh the last site feature I'll
mention is the landscaping.
Uh you'll see three street trees
proposed on Woodward Street. These will
be the first street trees on Woodward
Street. Um
>> and they are planted within a uh a small
planting strip that runs the length of
the frontage.
>> So there's no street trees on that
street
>> on Woodward Street. There's no street
trees. That's right.
>> So these will be the first three. And uh
on the theme of trees, our one waiver
requested uh which uh the shade tree
commission has uh already signified
approval of is regarding street trees.
Uh it's one ordinance section but sort
of a two-parter. Uh and that is not to
provide street trees on White Alley and
the second is for a reduced tree spacing
uh between two of the trees due to uh
some utility conflicts. Uh these lots
are on the uh the slim side. So to get
20 feet between each tree is is pretty
difficult here. Uh other past approvals
I'll mention uh namely is a zoning
variance uh that was granted in uh March
of 2024. Uh that allows a reduced front
width and uh lot width that is and um
lot area for the single family semi-
detached unit that we proposed lot three
here on the end. Um, instead of 25 feet
width and 2500 square feet, uh, we
proposed 24.83 feet width and 2,137
square ft, I believe. Uh, other
approvals we already have, uh, the city
has, u adopted the, u act 537 planning
for sewage and, uh, the department of of
environmental protection has already
accepted that as well.
Um, and lastly, I'll note that we've
been through a few uh rounds of review
with the city staff and their consultant
already. And at this point, um, the, uh,
comment letter from, uh, CSD Davidson
is, uh, mostly clean. Uh, barring a few
little, uh, plan notation updates and
little things like that. And at this
point, any questions about the plan, I'd
be happy to answer.
Miss Finn, you had said eminent domain
is happening at this property no matter
what.
So yes, the um the property the owner
has not complied with his rackal
agreement and had gone through a process
of um had he had received seven
extensions and had still not fulfilled
his requirements. And so last evening at
the um Rackle meeting uh they decided
that they would not provide another
extension thereby ending the contract um
for this property with Rackle.
>> So I guess my only question is what good
would even approving this plan do?
>> No, that's a good question. So um giving
this plan a conditional approval uh
would mean that is going to um go
through the process of having the
property um certified as blighted and
then we'll take it by eminent domain.
They will go through a process of um
providing just compensation to the owner
um and then they will resell the
property. They will find another owner
for the property. If all of that should
happen in one year, the new owner would
then have the option to fulfill the
conditions of the plan and to um record
the plan and they would have a land
development plan in their pocket. And so
that's I mean that's really the only
reasoning for it.
>> If I may, um I mean it's a valid
application that's been before us. It
meets all of the conditions of the
ordinance and today the the last day to
make a decision on it. And because it
meets all of those um requirements of
the ordinance, we have to recommend that
it be approved.
>> Okay. So, if I'm understanding right,
the the eminent domain processes are
going to happen one way or another. But
if this plan is approved, whomever
requires the property would have a land
development plan ready to go
>> potentially. Yes.
>> Does that does the timeline that you
noted earlier um also include the city
redevelopment um
I can't recall if this project um had or
was able to get to a rehab agreement
through the city reinvestment board.
>> I don't believe there was
>> um I there they started with a rehab
agreement through the property
reinvestment board and that did not um
go through. I think it was a previous
owner who had worked on that. Um and
then that's when it was determined
blighted again and then went back
um through like went through the process
of combination and blight.
>> Do you recall when the first initial
letter of blight was the eligible
letter?
>> Um yeah, it was discussed at the meeting
last night. I want to say it was um
>> at least the year was 2021 of when it
started the process.
>> 2021.
>> Yeah, I think it was 2022 when the whole
thing ended. Yep. So it's 2021 2022.
>> Have a question. Um so this is dividing
one parcel into three
that will be able to be done and the
blighted property will just be one of
those parcels. Is that correct?
>> And those other two would then be able
to be sold. Am I is am I tracking?
>> Well, so if
the subdivision goes along with the land
development.
>> Okay.
>> So they travel together.
>> They can't subdivide and then
And the city was um supportive of this
plan.
>> Yes.
>> And again the square footage on a single
unit is again
um the square foot of the footprint of
the two proposed units are 969 square
foot and 1,61 square feet and they're
two stories.
>> Any public comment?
approve.
>> Can I make a motion to approve the
preliminary final land development uh
plan for 523 Woodward Street?
>> Yeah, they have to meet the um the
requirements that were stated in their
last letter from CSD Davidson.
>> And you might want to make the like have
a motion on the modification request
before
>> the streets.
>> Yeah.
>> Unless you want to take the modification
request at the same time as the
>> What do you suggest is best? I would do
two separate motions.
>> Two separate motions.
>> Correct.
>> Okay.
Start with the trees.
I'll make a motion to approve a waiver
request for street trees for 523
Woodward Street.
>> Motion on the floor.
>> Ready for the question?
All in favor? That is known by saying I.
>> I.
>> I I
>> Motion carry.
Can I make a motion to approve the
preliminary final land development plan
for 523 Woodward Street
um with the notion that they will meet
all the requirements within the letter?
>> Second. Again, we have a motion on the
floor for 523 W Street.
Ready for the question
discussion?
All in favor let it known by saying I.
>> I
>> oppose hearing none. Motion carried.
Congratulations.
>> Thank you very much. Commissioners
Jones Motor Sports Preliminary final
land development conditional approval.
Good evening, Cheryl Love with the LA
Group. Um, we'll
review the plan briefly with you. Uh,
this is uh the existing building uh for
Jones Honda. It's located at 1335
Manheim Pike.
The building is rectangular in the back
portion of what you see rendered here.
Uh the existing footprint is about 5,000
square feet. Um they would renovate the
inside of that building, but there would
be an addition on the front of the
building. So the south side and the west
side and the addition would be about 7,2
there would be a 4,000 foot green roof
on top of the new portion of the
addition. So a large majority of the
addition
supporting storm water requirements
are on the roof
equipment and such. Um there are other
storm water areas that we are providing
with this plan. To the west of it,
there's some underground storm water
storage.
There is an area at the back that is an
existing grass area. Um some of the
green roof and some of the other
components will discharge into a swale
that exists back there. Uh we are
improving some
wetland Not, excuse me, but more meadow
habitat with native plantings within a
lot of the area at the rear area in that
grass space as well as providing
for trees, new trees in that area that
also provide some storm water in the
rear portion of the
trees
of the lighter colored ones on the on
the plant left side.
With regards to the uh remainder of the
site, it's it's minimal as far as our
disturbance and what we're doing. Uh we
are providing some additional landscape
bed areas around the building itself.
Some restriping of some parking areas.
Uh some sidewalk improvements out front.
We do have shade tree approval and their
support in what I'll shortly as a
modification request that relates to
Um along the property frontage there are
a number of signs of utilities as well
as driveways that exist
and within that space we've calculated
what we would need for street trees. So
based on the frontage we would need a
total of 16 new street trees. Um, we did
work through discussions with the SHA
tree commission meeting to provide for
trees.
I don't know if the landscape is panual.
Oops. I'm sorry.
Sorry.
If it keeps maybe you have to go down
which direction there keep going down
that the trees there. Um we do have
easements um out front that we are
providing for four street trees out
front. Um and then we're working the
rest of the trees in. We're adding trees
primarily along the back portion where
it's also um helps for improvement
within there's
general area along the back of the site
that is flood plane area on this uh
right end of the plan or the east end in
that grass space. So we're providing
some tree plantings in there as well all
while providing uh easements around all
of those trees for ensuring that those
remain in are required to do so.
So, we have um addressed most we're down
to most administrative style comments um
and we will continue to work through
those otherwise um
it's a pretty straightforward plan. Um I
believe we have met the storm water
needs and requirements other than uh we
have to share and provide an easement on
the green roof on the top of the
building which is not unusual for
green roofs to make sure those are
maintained in
the normal storm water agreements
agreements I think we have to settle on
security
we will work through those pieces,
you know, with staff. So, um, we've,
again, it's decently straightforward
from a plan standpoint, but we're
certainly
answering
Uh the only question I have, I
appreciate the easement. Uh why the
location? And part of why I asked is
because it looks like it was a curved
room. Kind of like looking for uh you
know, this is going to be a display
corner almost. Um I'm just saying this
for the sake of the developer. Like I
wouldn't want the trees to reduce their
sales prospects.
without cars anyway.
>> Well, that is also some of the
discussion we had with Shantibility
standpoint, but that's their sales
display area of their vehicles. And the
Shry Commission was
very supportive of allowing us to fit
the trees everywhere we could, which um
We are over some pavement. So, we are
getting still some uh heat reduction
effect in the rear portion, but that
area is more of a service area and not
so much a sales display area out front.
Um they do have a number of signs. There
are actually two buildings within this
one overall.
So, that's why this existing building is
is rendered lighter color. But our our
focus the project is really involving
the existing building in the rear which
is it's a very unappealing building
right now but it will greatly improve
the visual look of that as well from the
front while still supporting everything
we could for storm water on the new
structure the existing structure that
>> I I think I see them on the plan but
there are new sidewalks
are out. Wonderful. Yep. All across the
frontage. Um in fact, one of our prior
one of our prior landscape architects
did something for Jones Honda
to the west here. And in fact, at that
point, they were doing any street
improvements. So, we had to do some
convincing to the owner that this is
different. These are new ordinances.
These are requirements. Um we appreciate
that the shade tree commission is
supportive of um allowing us to provide
an ement
which also enhances that plan area back
there and some of the plantings in there
without impacting the owner's use of the
front space for his sales.
So they understand they understand
uh I did not mention five trees didn't
fit
as well that's all out
which we comply with the commission
Any
comment from the commission?
Any public comment?
Hearing none.
I'll make a motion to approve the
modific modification request um for
street trees for motor sports.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion and a second
floor.
Any further discussion?
All in favor let known by saying I
>> I
>> oppose.
Eyes have hearing none. Eyes have it.
Congratulations.
I think we need the second part.
I'll also make a motion to approve the
preliminary final final land development
and for final land development plan for
Jones Motorsports with the commissions
in the water.
>> Second
motion on the floor and a second. All in
favor that known by saying I
>> I
Thank you.
>> Thank you for your time tonight.
>> Thank you.
>> Thanks for your patience.
>> Other business
self storage
tech amendment
and zoning map.
Thank you for your patience.
>> Good evening. I'm Claudia Shank with MC
Wallace and Nur. I'm here this evening
on behalf of 1031 Dillerville Road LP.
I'm joined this evening by Jim Buer with
David Miller Associates who is the uh
land planner for this project. Eric
Scott who is here on behalf of the
developer which is an affiliate of Oak
Tree Development.
Nate Jones with Storage Construction who
would be designing and building the
proposed building for this property. and
Alyssa Quill uh with storage asset
management who would be providing
on-site management services for this
project. I did pass out uh a copy of the
exhibits. They're also on the screen,
but to avoid you having to look over
your shoulder, you have a hard copy
there in front of you. Exhibit one in
the packet is the property that brings
us here this evening. Uh it's an aerial
map of the site and what we're talking
about is a two roughly two and a half
acre unit planned community unit within
a two-unit planned community known as
the Dillerville Road Site Association.
So the second unit there is the building
that you see immediately to the south of
the property that's highlighted in blue.
The property is primarily located in the
city's C3 regional commercial zoning
district. There is a small portion of
the property that is in the central
manufacturing zoning district. If you
turn to exhibit two in your packet,
you'll see an excerpt of the zoning map.
The orientation is slightly different
from uh exhibit one. But you can see
there again highlighted in blue is the
property we're discussing and the pink
being the C3 and the light gray which
encompasses a very small portion of the
property and the land to the north would
be the manufacturing zoning district or
the CM district. The property is
currently improved with a commercial
building which is leased to an
automotive repair shop and several out
buildings. Uh it's located along
Dillerville Road.
We have been working on a proposed
redevelopment of this site for a number
of years and have been in consultation
with city staff about that. Uh there are
some site constraints that make this a
challenging property to redevelop. Most
notably, and you can see this most
clearly on exhibit one, the property
does not have any direct direct street
access. So, it actually gains access to
Dillerville Road via an easement over uh
the adjoining shopping center to the
south of the property. So, as a result
of that, we've been sensitive to the
need to find a use for this property
that would have relatively low trip
generation, and that is how we landed on
a self- storage facility as the proposed
use.
Self- storage facilities are not
permitted in the C3 district. They are
permitted in the adjoining CM district.
And so uh we are asking as part of our
request to extend the CM zoning district
to encompass this property. In addition,
the facility that we're proposing to
build is a little bit different than
what I'll call a traditional drive up
self-s storage facility. It's more in
keeping with current trends to build
taller facilities with more interior
access to units. Uh and the zoning
ordinance, the city zoning ordinance
doesn't really contemplate that kind of
facility. So currently the ordinance
would limit all facilities to 20,000
square feet or less and the facility
we're proposing to develop would be
three stories and about 120,000 square
feet. So we're proposing to in addition
to the resoning to modify the
regulations in the CM district to allow
for a facility of this type in certain
circumstances within the CM district.
And we did work extensively with staff
on developing the criteria that would
need to be met in order for this type of
a facility to be developed in the CM
district specifically. So I'll just run
through those quickly now. So first of
all, the property on which the facility
is constructed would need to be between
three and seven acres. You may have
heard me mention that this condo unit or
plan community unit is only two and a
half acres, but the overall property um
that the the tax parcel that the
property uh includes is is within those
measurements between three and seven
acres and would qualify under the
proposed amendment. The building has to
be climate controlled. Most of the
building has to be three two or more
stories except for drive up units
located along the first floor of the
building. All the units would need to be
accessed from the interior of the
building and there is uh careful
thinking in terms of exterior garage
doors along the frontage. They have to
be separated in some fashion from the
street in the form of a burm, a screen,
some other buffering.
Any outdoor storage of boats or vehicles
has to be in the side or rear yard. Must
be on a paved surface. The building
needs to be enclosed with the security
fence. uh there can be parking outside
the fence but access to the building
needs to be restricted in that fashion.
We have explored throughout the lifetime
of this project which again has been
several years the possibility of
allocating a portion of the building for
some kind of a a community space. We're
not exactly sure what that looks like at
this point in time. Um I will share with
you that the building that is on the
second planned community unit or
immediately to the south of this site
was recently sold to Heck Construction.
So, we have had some conversation with
them about, you know, could they use
some space within the building for some
kind of an apprenticeship program or a
training program. Again, nothing has
been finalized, but we did did build
into this amendment some flexibility to
allow for appropriate accessory uses
within a self-s storage building that
may not be, you know, things that would
be typically incidental to a self-s
storage use. So things like game courts,
public or private meeting rooms,
training rooms, and and other similar
uses would be permitted uh as an
accessory use. In addition, city staff
has expressed a desire as part of this
process to incorporate design standards
that would apply to all buildings in the
CM district, not just self storage that
are greater than 50,000 square feet. So
we wrote those design standards as
prepared by city staff into ordinance.
They focus primarily on architectural
requirements for building entrances,
facades, and roofs. And really, they're
designed to ensure that buildings are
are visually interesting, have some
differentiation of materials, facade
treatments, and the like. um sharing
with you now. Uh if you turn to exhibit
three in your packet, you'll see three
photographs of storage facilities that
were uh constructed by storage
construction.
These are just meant to be examples of
what has been done in other places. We
do not have a design for this building
at this point in time, but this shows
the variation that can be achieved and
certainly the flexibility in terms of
complying with design requirements like
the ones that will now be in your
ordinance if the amendment is approved.
The first photograph is a site in
Mckenji and Lehi County. If you want to
go to the second or scroll down to the
second one, that's a York facility with
the movein self storage. And then
finally, the third one is in Montgomery
County and Kmar. Again, just giving you
a feel for the different types of facade
treatments that can be accomplished to
create some visual interest.
Uh, at this point, I would like to turn
the presentation over to Jim Ber and let
him walk you a little bit through the
site plan. Of course, we recognize that
what we're asking for here in the in
terms of the text amendment doesn't just
apply to our property, but we still want
to um cover for you what what we're
planning to do with our site if the text
amendment is approved.
>> Okay. Yes. Uh we had uh prepared a site
uh concept plan uh indicating how the
the property could be developed under
the under the proposed uh resoning and
text amendment. Um as as Claudia had
mentioned the uh the parcel we're
looking at it was um unit B of the plan
plant community which on the sketch is
shown in basically a pink background. So
um you know as she mentioned there' be
the removal of the existing automobile
service building and one of the other
out buildings and then the proposed uh
self storage facility would be in the
center of the site. work on this
concept. We're showing it as 200 by 200
feet. Um, in addition to the building
construction, uh, there'll be some
reconfiguration of the parking and
storage areas and also the addition of
two gates to secure the outside storage.
And those gates are between the building
and road and then building and the rear
of the property. They're labelled there.
I'm not sure if you can see them or not.
And those gates are like I said to
provide security for the outside storage
which would be permitted in the side and
rear rear yard.
In addition, you can see in the on the
concept plan the yellow hatched area is
the access that Claudia mentioned and
that is a recorded access agreement.
both.
And as far as utilities, uh the site is
currently served by existing public
water and public sewer and the uh
existing laterals run from the rear of
the property out to Harrisburg Avenue.
And finally, parking. We did show some
projected parking there.
may be some adjustments as we work
through the design, but we would provide
enough parking to meet the requirements
of the city ordinance.
And also storm water management. Um, at
this point, we're only at the conceptual
stage, so we don't have any storm water
management design figured out, but that
would be a part of the project. Although
that being said, most of the site is
impous
to briefly cover some of the planning
justifications that we believe exist for
the request. So again, the property
already adjoins land that's in the CM
zoning district. It's really an
extension of that adjoining district.
The city's comprehensive does identify
this property as being suitable for
general commercial or industrial use
which is what's being proposed here. Uh
the design standards again which which
were initiated by the city are also
compliant and in keeping with the
comprehensive plan that encourages
ensuring compatibility of building
design with the local context the
surrounding area. And then finally, both
the city's plan and and the county plan
emphasized the importance of converting
underutilized properties to to a more
viable use. And we believe after much
thought that that this is an appropriate
and viable use for this site. So, we're
happy to answer any questions you have.
I do just want to point out again,
Alyssa and Nate, that are with us that
have the expertise in operating these
facilities and constructing these
facilities. So, if there are specific
questions going to those items, I'll
I'll defer those to them.
And I I should say our request from you
this evening is a recommendation to city
council that they approve the amendment
to the map and text.
Um I think that you're making sense to
me.
Uh I do have concerns about allowing
more by right self storage facilities
though in the community. Um just a
personal view. I view self storage
facilities as a cancer on long-term
property values. Um, but I can recognize
the constraints you're experiencing with
this site. Um, have you considered
instead of reszoning and permitting more
by right self storage, maybe special
exception use for the zone you're
currently in? So that at least like
there's more conversation because I
think this makes sense. Yeah, this I we
basically arrived at this resolution
after I want to say over a year of
conversations with city staff in terms
of yeah, Eric saying years of what we
wanted versus what the city wanted. I
think we actually started out with
something that was more narrowly
tailored to this site and staff had
recommended that we open it up a little
bit. So, I appreciate your comment,
understand where you're coming from. I
think this is it's been a collaborative
effort and that's how we ended up where
we are.
Any
further comment from the commission?
Any public comment?
Lauren, I'm just wondering if you can
give the city's perspective on this and
particularly
uh in response comment about Sounds like
the city wants more is in favor of more
of this type of use.
>> I will I will defer to Betsy, but first
I will also say that I would not I would
not characterize characterize it as the
city is in favor of more
use of property for self storage. I
think that we were working to find the
use um for this
for this space in this district. Um but
I will Betsy worked much more on the
text amendment than I did, so I will
defer to her.
>> Thanks, Lauren. Um yeah, so we did a
pretty in-depth analysis of looking at a
variety of different um options for how
big of a parcel it would be would be
considered a good idea for that. indoor
self storage especially is the current
trend right now. We anticipate that we
would get more applications for it. Um
currently our ordinance allows this type
of use at 20,000 square feet or less in
the R3 and R4 and as part of this um
ordinance we're getting that removed.
That's that's how the self storage ended
up in this um Sycamore Ridge and because
they just went through the special
exception process. Um I understand your
your comments about going through the
special exception process. I think
generally my analysis since I've started
here is that we have a lot of things
that require a special exception that
maybe don't necessarily need to have a
special exception which increases the
volume that zoning hearing board gets.
So I think if we have the correct
standards that are in place then if they
wanted to do something different they
could go through that process
and part of those correct standards is a
minimum acreage according to what I'm
read
what we're looking at is a minimum
acreage
>> correct that's correct so it's not like
somebody's going to come right
>> yeah and I'm happy to provide like the
breakdown that we did um we really
looked at like if it was three to five
acres, how many parcels would that
impact in the CM district currently if
it was 3 to seven? If it was two to five
and two, like two acres with no max. So,
we came to the conclusion that the least
impactful would be the 3 to seven acres,
but also allowing the CM district to be
developed if needed.
>> Do you have a map of the city with the
CM district? Like, how much area is CM?
>> Yeah, I don't I don't know. can pull one
up, but you're talking about the
periphery of the city. So, I think
another idea here is to to try to get
the self storage out of the core of the
city and the residential districts where
you may have people leasing garages and
that kind of thing. And ideally, the
larger facilities around the periphery
would take some of that pressure off.
I guess I'm just interested to know if
we this recommendation this evening how
what um effects this will have for other
particular parcels because like murk I'm
just I'm not familiar with the CM map
district. Yeah, I think if Lauren
Lauren's getting close to pulling it up.
So I think that might be helpful and
just seeing which ones are um CM. It's
obviously not going to provide you with
guidance on lot sizes for these you know
the the large mass of projects. So, as
um Claudia referenced, the majority of
these, it's the um lighter gray are on
the periphery. They're inexed areas of
the city. Um there are some along CM is
along Manor Street, which um was where
Kendler was at as well as a couple
little sections um if you can see off of
Cabbage Hill and then to the north um
East Walma and um
that portion.
I did calculate the amount to apply to
the county, but I don't like the total
acreage, but I don't have that off the
top of my head.
I think one of our biggest concerns with
the self- storage is that it was being
allowed in the R3 and the R4. Um, I
think as you you know, obviously the
city is older and there's a lot of kind
of dilapidated self storage like roads
that um probably aren use of that area
of the property.
And just to note like the R4 and the R3
are like the darker yellow.
So in comparison to just industrial
it's fairly significant where they would
be allowed as a special exception.
>> So for
given the
requirements like I'm looking at like
Engleside or like the former Kinsler
property. Are those
>> So the Kunzler site is I think 28
acres. Um we just looked at that. That
wasn't on the plate when we've been
working on this for quite a while. I
think I met with them the first week I
started to be honest.
>> Um so that wasn't really like on the
radar at that point in time.
Yeah, I mean I I agree with not wanting
storage facilities in R3 and R4. I just
don't I don't know that I'm supportive
of making it easier to build these kinds
of facilities. I mean it it seems like
it makes sense for this site, but you
know they don't they don't create many
jobs. They don't, you know, they don't
foster like pedestrian activity like and
even in I mean even in this site like
you are right next to like strip mall
that you know that has some pedestrian
activity. So, I don't know. I I I'm
would be concerned about allow like
allow making it easier to use
districts.
I think that they should be permissible,
but I think that they should kind of be
like last resorts. And I I can
understand your point about the zoning
hearing board having a huge load. Um,
but hopefully we can reduce some of that
load with the overall comprehensive plan
updates that we need to make.
>> Um, I I would take great reservation
with approving self storage by right in
these zones, but I do agree with
eliminating it in the R3 and R4.
Further comment
I think the commission should consider a
motion to maybe table this so that more
like individual retrospection can be
done about it
but I can't make that motion. So that's
what I'm saying.
>> How's the city what's the city's um
stance?
Um, we went through several iterations
of this draft ordinance um to get it to
the point where it's at. And so at this
time, the city's in support of it.
I guess considering some of my fellow
commissioners thought I
do agree that
I think what I'm not clear on is how
this decision today will affect
and how that will affect the
I don't have I don't have a list in
front of me but there are other
properties where this could occur. I
want to say it's maybe in the range of
10 or 15 other properties where it would
be theoretically possible. Now many of
those properties if not all of them are
already developed but in theory you know
somebody could redevelop them for this
use. Um so that possibility does exist.
I I
yeah what the analysis we did with that
there's 25 parcels that would meet these
size requirements um and that five of
them are vacant land everything else is
in existing use
>> it's a great question I did this
analysis several months ago and not
finding the map that I provided with it
so I'd also be interested to know how
this aligns with the
comp plan
from our future
perspective
in addition to the comments Claudia
already provided regarding it.
>> Yeah, I just from like
what is that area in the comp plan? Did
you say that? And I'm sorry.
>> Yeah. Yes. It's it's the the our parcel
in the comp plan is general commercial
industrial is is the the goal for the
future use. But it's being limited to to
just the areas that are
designated for these types of uses, not
residential areas, not commercial areas.
Frankly,
we also look to see if it would have any
issues with um the surrounding parcels
that are located in Manhattan Township.
They are zoned similarly. They're a mix
of industrial and commercial uses.
Um so, it would be another like
transition phase. It would just be
extending it It's not like a random spot
that isn't tied to existing industrial.
>> So if we Yep.
>> through these couple years of analysis
when you get it down to five properties,
it's going to be very similar situations
to ours where
if self storage development is not
permitted, you're going to wind up with
what we had. a dilapidated partial site
with you know our lease is going to end
in February with Elliot's garage we have
two quant it's going to be an eyesore
that is what this text amendment will
unlock on a very very small scale I
really think it's smart land planning
and use of the sites so I just want you
know after a couple years of analysis
that's really what you're left with
>> what is the current process if this
isn't approved. Is it just going to
zoning and getting special exception or
something?
>> Um, if they were to to build the size
storage facility that they want to build
at that site, they would need to go
through the variance process. So, it
wouldn't just be special exception
because our ordinance doesn't discuss
self storage beyond the 20,000 square
feet. So, they would need a variance to
exceed that by
>> 150%.
for storage.
>> I think now's probably the right time.
The answer, the short answer, yes.
>> It's popping up everywhere. It's an
eyesore.
I'm not
concerned about
>> you come up please. Thank you.
>> And I can plot the exact numbers. right
now in Lancaster, we manage 600 storage
facilities, but I live right here in
Lancaster. Um, and in uh the supply of
self storage in the state of
Pennsylvania is about eight square feet
per capita in Lancaster
within and people use storage within a
three mile radius of where they live.
So, you've got a lot of people downtown
and really only a handful of very small
self- storage properties nearby. the
occupancy is very high and the rates are
really high because they're full. Um, so
the I think the supply I'll find the
number, but it's 4.1
square feet per capita. The estimated
demand is nine square feet per capita.
So people downtown are driving much
further away uh to find the space and
they're paying a lot more than they need
to. So this is a very relative to many
markets I look at across the country.
This is very underserved.
>> I think what's happening
really does push supply.
I think it's a smart idea, especially in
the location. I mean, your trap
constraints are valid. F&M's right
there, though, so the students probably
could utilize that property a lot uh for
self storage. But I think I don't think
anyone up here is concerned about this
specific proposal. It's just a concern
about what other proposals might come
from it. Uh in the interim of like like
I said earlate,
which isn't your fault. Um, so I'd like
to see you move forward, but I I also
think there is a need for pause. That's
just my opinion.
Right? If we if we were to go down to
like three to five acres um for example,
then it would be 16 parcels, three of
which are vacant land. So that would
reduce the number of par parcels that
would be impacted. Um which I think is
honestly what they provided originally
and we after doing analysis were looking
at places like where it would be
appropriate use. Jal and I went through
every parcel that was zoned and in that
um size range to determine if it would
be acceptable and that's how we came to
that number.
>> I apologize. Can you remind me what is
the acreage of this parcel
because I agreed I love the idea there
but if Kunler somebody buys it and buys
just a little piece extra and suddenly
they have 3.2 acres do we have a storage
unit on man street sort of thing. So
that's again my concern to um
and I was going to say could we go up to
five to seven acres but you're saying
this parcel is not going to
>> Yeah. And I would note that uh the
zoning hearing board recently approved a
um storage self storage facility down by
um Price Elementary that's double the
size of what's allowed and it's on a
twoacre site. Um the city did
um disagree with that decision decision,
but the zoning hearing board made that
decision.
Mr. Chair,
I believe we have, not to it or diminish
the commentary we have here, but I do
believe we have enough information to
bring a motion before the board.
>> I agree.
>> May I make that motion?
>> Yes. I make a motion to bring before the
city council um to recommend the self
storage text amendment and zoning map.
Amendment as delineated by example for
I just note procedurally if there's no
second then the motion would die.
>> Okay, there is a motion on the floor but
there is no second
Sorry. So that's your Lauren. So our
options basically are to approve or
reject.
>> I mean you can recommend changes that
you would like to see to it. Um
>> we just do the exact number of acres.
Could
we table this motion and collect more
information from the city to understand
how this could really affect other
parcels? Like I know that you said that
there's a number of other parcels that
could potentially um do this. I would be
interested to know where those parcels
are located and um what the buildable
what the opportunities are on them for
that. and then revisit this
conversation. I think that's my
preferred method to proceed without
having the process start all over again.
I'm curious
the transportation constraints as like
it's by right but if there's a for
example no frontage accessible by the
road I'm curious
because I I
Why did this process take so long to
begin with? Not to believe this meeting
any longer than it already is. But it
just seems like that's a long time to
work on a text amendment. So I'm just
curious to know why it would that long
so far. Why this decision made sooner so
Mr. Scott wouldn't be in this position
where Whether this this decision tonight
would be detrimental to the decision.
Continue
discuss
happy.
Yeah, I mean I think that part of like
the transition.
>> Could you give us a month?
>> Okay.
I don't know what
to number.
C can you repeat your compromise because
you
>> repeat that again?
I think we proposed to
>> city
language about
access.
>> Okay.
>> Right.
>> We don't want competitors.
If
>> if we would make a recommendation to
proceed with this um under the notion
that we consider the addition additional
terms of adding the street frontage
language to it, how does that affect the
other parcels that could that are
located with like closer within the
city? We we didn't do an analysis on
frontage when we were looking at the
parcels. So we
>> You mean street access,
>> not frontage.
But I mean I I also don't know that it's
best practice to create a text amendment
that's really catered toward
>> I mean that's really what the what the
variance process is for. So I guess I'm
So, the the storage facility that you
said the zoning hearing board just
approved, what was what variance were
they requesting?
>> Um, I would say that's a little bit
It was a variance to exceed the 20,000
square feet by think
like 39,000 square feet. So it was
double the size. I think there was some
uh
setback variances
um and then also variance to not do the
bicycle parking
right against the trail. One of the
reasons I wanted to bring it to vote a
is we need two, right? But the other
thing is if this was residential, we'd
be ecstatic that they're using that kind
of density for that property. I mean,
this is 120,000 square feet and you're
like, "Oh my gosh, who really needs
that?" But again, they're not wasting
that space. It's not a suburban spraw.
It is something that kind of fits what
the city should be requesting of any
commercial whatever this is under thing.
So that's plus by recommending it to
city council. Yes, it does have our
stamp on it, but they're going to the
public's on you know they left two hours
ago but they will have public at the
city council meeting if they want to
chime in and override anything we
decided that's there. Um I don't expect
a second. It already happened but
reason behind it. I think it's so clear
on the plan what they want to do. It's
just a matter of do we want to see that?
>> I agree with Mr. Still. This isn't best
practice, but I also think best pra best
practice left us when we're two years
past the comprehensive update. Um I I
think this is a very reasonable
compromise if we add the language about
the street front restriction, but that's
just my opinion. If I could make the
motion, I would.
Do we have another motion on the floor?
So, if you were going to if somebody was
going to make another motion, you would
need to make the motion
>> um with the um conditions that you've
just proposed. Just so that we're clear.
Just
>> clarify.
>> And that was to reduce the size the lot
size
>> the lot size to three to five acres and
um parcels without direct access to
public streets.
Okay, I will make that motion for self
storage text amendment and zoning map
amendment with the conditions to reduce
the size of 3 to 5 acres
language and public access to the
I can.
We have a motion on the floor.
Second
further discussion.
>> I'm so sorry. I'm just confused. Why are
we lessening the acreage? Don't we want
to increase the acreage?
>> The lessening of the acreage will make
it apply to less lots.
>> Less lots. So by by going from instead
of it being three to seven acres, it
being three to five, it will include
less lots.
>> Yeah. It would impact
>> 10 less develop like 10 less parcels,
two of which would be vacant. So So the
impact would be 16 parcels available,
three vacant, but that doesn't include
an analysis of the frontage. And as
Claudia said, she did that. So it only
probably one other person.
Further discussion.
All in favor known by saying I.
>> I.
>> I I
oppose.
Nay.
>> Nay.
>> Eyes have it. Motion carry.
Congratulations.
>> Number six, uh, staff report.
>> Nope.
>> Number seven.
>> Thank you. It's bedtime.
>> Number seven, public comment.
None.
>> Motion to adjurnn.
>> And number eight,
>> we have motion to adjurnn. We have a
second. All in favor by saying I.
Eyes have it. Motion carries. Second.
>> No. Who did that?